Okay, good morning. Uh, welcome back.
Any questions or comments from uh
yesterday?
Uh, yes.
>> Uh, yeah, I I did a I I got went down a
rabbit hole about Ulisses. Um, and it's
it's rife in in the academic sources
about like nobody really agrees on what
Ulyses is doing in there and why all
academics seem to be contingent on this.
Um, he's in the he's in the realm of
false counselors
and he obviously he went on the the boat
trip um and convinced his men we need to
go to the end of the world and he gave
false counselor to them. But it's just a
boatload of men. There's no reason why
giving false counselor to to 50 people
would end him in this level of hell. And
when the few places that they seem to be
in agreement on is that through Homer
and then Ver Virgil Zenid and then
Dante's Inferno, he ends up to to Dante
himself, he's essentially giving counsel
to the ages on go beyond your means.
Have this what is it? this um
this god-like pride to go beyond God's
limits like what Adam ends up doing. Um
and
some academics have him as like um he's
suffering for Dante sin because Dante
has this arrogance that you keep
speaking about. And so they they find
certain points in the in the Kanto to to
really point that out. But I thought it
was important because I had a college
professor who spoke about Lord Alfred
Tennyson's poem on Ulisses, right?
>> And it finishes with uh Ulysus is an old
man. And he's sitting with his his son
Telmachus and he's like uh oh I'm so
sad. And the final line is I'm made weak
by time and fate but strong in will to
strive to seek to find and not to yield.
And Tennyson is essentially doing what
Homer has done, which is like maybe
there's some there's some nobility in in
both, but you're sitting next to your
son who you've abandoned your whole
life, man. Like like appreciate your son
and quit quit going on out.
>> And um he this college professor brought
it up because that final quote would be
on uh pictures on students walls with
like the moon landing and stuff and they
would and students were like, "Yeah, get
it. like always go out, go beyond your
means, be Victor Frankenstein. Um, and
he's like, humanity's taking the wrong
message that everybody has been trying
to tell us now. And so it's it's
effective. Dante puts him there because
he essentially is a false counselor to
all of humanity up until today.
>> Right. Okay. All right. So that's really
interesting. Um, so let me make some
comments. First of all, Ulysis is there
where he has been punished not because
uh he's he sailed away from his family.
It's because of the Trojan horse, right?
So he counled the Greeks uh to devise
the Trojan horse and that's what he's
punished for and that's pretty explicit
in the divine comedy. Uh that's point
one. Okay. not not for misleading his
men to their deaths but for uh advising
the Greeks to use a Trojan horse uh
which destroyed Troy which is um which
and they they are the uh ancestors to
the Romans. That's point one. Point two
is like what we need to remember is that
at this time in history Donn does not
have access to Homer.
Uh he knows Ulisses through the Iniad.
Uh because in the Yinyat it says
explicitly that Ulisses advised the
Greeks on the Trojan horse, him and
Damedes, and that's why they're
suffering together. Um point three is
that if you actually read Homer's
Odyssey, it's a very different take on
uh Odysius. Um I've taught the Odyssey
and the the Odyssey is ultimately not
about a journey outward, but a journey
home to his family. and he comes home
and he realizes that what really matters
is family and it's a family reunion. So
it goes counter it's really interesting
but it goes counter to the popular
western narrative that Ulissi is he is a
romantic wanderer or explorer. Um so um
what I should have done is actually
taught Homer then taught Virgil then
taught Dante because there it's a
straight legacy. Okay. Uh Virgil's
responding to Homer and then Dant is
responding to Virgil. And what's really
interesting is that Dante never read
Homer. Uh because at this time uh you
can't access the Greek, but Homer and
Dante agree on everything. So it's
almost like Dant is the second coming of
Homer. So it's really interesting that
that that way.
>> Okay.
>> Uh yes. Maybe um Virgil intentionally
tried to make home and the Odyssey look
bad because they wanted to or he wanted
to kill the Greek culture, right? So he
wanted to replace it with the Roman
culture and so he can like he talks bad
about the Odyssey and
>> Exactly. And and this was something
we'll go more into later on. But
remember from last class we talked about
how the counterfeitter was uh arguing
with Son the the man who tricked the
Trojans in the land letting in the
Trojan horse. They were arguing who is
worse and it was Virgil who created St.
s on right so basically if you think
about it if you just use your
imagination
um there's a counterfeit counterfeiting
of coin and then there's a
counterfeiting of poetry right so what
he's really saying is okay m I'm saying
to son hey maybe I counterfeited coin
but you counterfeited someone's
poetry you plagiarize someone's poetry
is that much worse than counterfeiting
uh coins because at this time in history
remember counterfeitting coins is a
really serious crime especially in
Florence because they're very proud of
um their currency which which considered
pure gold right so um we we'll go back
that section but but yeah just but but
that's a good point okay any more points
yes
>> uh so last night I was reading a journal
entry by Manley P Hall
>> right yes
>> and it's just
>> the cultist
>> yeah and it's his commentary on on the
divine comedy and what I thought was
interesting relating to the question we
discussed towards the end of class about
why is hell frozen and there's it's not
not moving is he separately not related
to that question says and I quote
motional desire or restlessness is the
unsatisfied impulse of all creation to
reach identity with the divine motion
must continue until no interval remains
between consciousness and the infinite
and then a few sentences later says
Man is the self moved by the power of
will and desire. So if we if we think of
then hell again, if there's no movement
and it's all frozen, then surely that
implies that it's because we're so deep
in the inferno that there is so little
uh will and desire and you're so far
from connecting with the divine.
>> Yeah, exactly. They basically given up
on themselves, right? So it's really
interesting. Uh, and I'll point out that
um, oultists do read Divine Comedy
literally. Like they they really believe
that um, Donnie had a near-death
experience or he had visions of the
after afterlife and they do take him
literally. And today we will go into
demetic possession, which is something
that they're really concerned about,
right? Is it possible to possess by
angels and demons? And Dante refers to
this um, in inferno and we'll discuss
this in depth, okay? But yeah, their
cult is really important idea. A cultist
love Dante. Um any Yes.
>> Um yeah. So yesterday I thought more
about the Dante putting people who
hijack our imagination lower than people
who murder someone and
>> or commit genocide, right? Committed
genocide and like Yes. Um, and so what I
don't understand is that does murdering
not like kill someone's entire capacity
to imagine anything because you can't
imagine if you're in hell or in in
paradise, right? Like you can't because
you you don't have a body and you don't
have like worldly experiences. So like
you can't imagine at all. And like if
you hijack the imagination. Okay. But
but like you can still like get your
imagination back if it's hijacked,
right? But you can't get it back if you
dead.
>> Yeah.
>> So does like a follow-up question would
be if Dante believes in reincarnation
maybe. So that's like a solution to
that.
>> Okay. Yeah. So D does say there's
reincarnation
um in paradise when Beatatrice is
talking to him and saying look your
souls are immortal right that that's
explicit in divine comedy your souls are
mortal so Dar does believe in the um uh
in in the immortality of the soul um but
to answer your question what's really
important to understand is that for
Dante
hell earth and heaven correspond on with
each other and what's really important
is to maintain the dynamic creativity of
the universe. Basically maintains
maintain our capacity to imagine. Okay?
Because that's a life force of the
universe.
And um when you reduce people from the
world that that doesn't actually reduce
the imag life force from the world
because it's possible that a few people
um have the imagination right so Dante
is very imaginative and he's able to
change society through his imagination.
for one person. As long as this one
person maintains his capacity for
imagination, the entire universe still
revolves. Okay? It still moves.
The problem with counterfeiting or
hijacking the imagination is that you're
reducing the universe's overall capacity
to be imaginative. Okay? Does that make
sense? So, so, so this is a
counterintuitive idea, but what matters
is not the sum total of life in the
universe. What matters is a sum total of
imagination in the universe. And when
you counterfeit the imagination and
disrupt the um connection between
humanity and the divine then that
reduces the the overall imagination in
the universe and therefore it reduces
the total life force in the universe.
Yes.
>> So if Dante would have been killed then
there would have been another Dante at
some point probably.
>> Um exactly. I I think I think that's
what Dante would say. But at the same
time, and he's explicit about this,
right? He is on a divine mission, right?
In hell, he doesn't have to fear the
demons. He doesn't have to fear uh
anything because God has willed it,
right? So when he wrote the divine
comedy, he's like, I don't fear dying
halfway and not completing divine
comedy. I don't fear my marriage being
burned. I don't fear being the script
because God has willed it. You
understand? And it's this complete faith
that allows him to access the vine and
complete the divine comedy. This
something that Manny Hall would say as
well, right? Okay. Uh yes. What was it
that allowed Faronata to imagine that
his son was dead in that if the Satan
frozen in the bottom of the hell cannot
imagine anything? What mechanism was it
that allowed Faronata to because I
remember that he says that he cannot
notice things that are close to them but
can sense things that are long past or
long to come. If in hell imagination is
stripped away, how could what mechanism
did Dante leverage to get Faronata to
believe that Guido was dead?
>> Right. That's a really good point. Okay,
so um this is a really hard question and
I I'll try my best, but I think there's
a difference between the imagination and
the emotion. Okay, the emotion is is
your connection with other people.
You're longing for your son, your
longing for your wife, the long you're
longing for for God. Okay, and the
emotion can never be extinguished
because it's tied to the soul.
So um even though Feronata doesn't have
the capacity to imagine he does have the
capacity to long for his son right and
that's why when Donnie said to him your
son is burning in hell it's so
anguishing for uh Feronato because no no
it was not Fernato it's coverante okay
it's cover kee um and he um lacks the
imagination to think that Donnie could
could be could be lying Okay, here in
hell it's not possible for the souls to
imagine that others could be deceiving
them. Um, and so he falls into
tremendous anguish. Okay, does that make
sense? There's a difference between the
the imagination and the emotion. Love,
right? Love is the unifying force of the
universe. The imagination is the
animating force of the universe. And um
the imagination is unique to us. And the
imagination is only is only available to
those with a body. Okay. All right. So,
good question. And uh again, like
scholars have been debating these
questions for hundreds of years,
literally. Okay. You're going to find
like hundreds of different commentaries
online about Dante. So, all all we're
doing is we're speculating here. Okay.
Um anymore. This is great, by the way.
Uh yes.
So, it's got me thinking because
everybody in hell doesn't want to be in
hell. So, there's a there's a difference
between imagination and desire. They all
desire for it to stop or is there like
is there something going on there?
>> Well, if you remember when they are
crossing the Aaron River to come going
to hell, they desire it. I mean, Donnie
is explicit here. Remember the word
desire, right? Uh and Donnie is
surprised by this. Like, why are people
desiring to go to hell? And the only
reason why is they think they deserve
it. They think they think it's a release
from whatever sin they they've done. And
it's something that we'll discuss later
on where
um if you if you think that dementic
possession is possible, right? Then you
also have to think that interdimensional
uh travel is possible. You have to think
that the soul can exist in different
dimensions. And when you do anything whe
whether it's virtuous or whe whether
it's sinful
you your sin can uh tra t trespass into
other dimensions. Okay. So like so like
when you do something sinful your your
soul is now locked in hell for in a
certain place and and that that's what
Dante is suggesting here where if you
think about it okay the person commits
uh a sin of lust and now he's in the
plane of lust. Are you saying that's the
only sin he committed? Are you saying he
did nothing else with his life? But but
but what I think Donnie is suggesting is
like the sin uh it corrupts a soul in a
certain way so that the soul is trapped
in a certain plane of hell. But to
understand that you need to also believe
in the infinite dimensions of the soul
and the fact that the soul across exists
across infinite dimensions and where
whatever you do u the soul becomes more
anchored in certain dimension if that
makes any sense. Okay. And again if you
read many Paul the occultist he does go
into this. Okay.
Okay. Great. Yeah. Okay. Let's let let's
continue please. Okay, we're at candle
>> line 25.
The denube where it flows in Austria,
the dawn beneath its frozen sky, have
never made for their course to so thick
a veil in winter as there was here. For
had Mount Tabernick or Propana's
mountain crashed upon it, not even that
the edge would it have creaked. And as
the croaking frog sits with its muzzle
above the water, in the season when the
peasant woman often dreams of gleaning,
so livid in the ice, up to the place
where shame can show itself were those
sad shades whose teeth were chattering
with note like stors.
Each kept his face bent downward
steadily. Their mouth bore witness to
the cold they felt just as their eyes
proclaimed their sorrow hearts. When I
had looked around a while, my eyes
turned toward my feet and saw two locked
so close the hair upon their heads had
intermingled.
"Do tell me, you whose chests are
pressed so tight," I said, "Who are
you?" They bent back their necks, and
when they'd lifted up their faces toward
me, their eyes which wept upon
[clears throat] the ground before, shed
tears down on their lips until the cold
held fast the tears and locked their
lids still more. No clamp has ever
fastened plank to plank so tightly. And
because of this they butted each other
like two rams such was their fury. And
one from whom the cold had taken both as
ears who kept his face bent low and
said, "Why do you keep on staring so at
us? If you would like to know who these
two are at that valley where Benzio
descends belong to them and to their
father Alberto.
They came out of one body and you can
search all ca you'll never find a shade
more fit to sit within this ice. Not him
who at one blow had chest and shadow
shattered by Arthur's hand. And not
Fukacia and not the sinner here who so
impeded my vision with his head. I can't
see past him. His name was Cassul
Mascaroni. If you're Tusca now you know
who he has been.
Unless you keep me talking any longer,
know that I was commission de poty. I'm
waiting for Carino to absolve me. And
after that, I saw a thousand faces made
doglike by the cold for which I shudder
and always will when I face frozen fors.
And while we were advancing toward the
center to which all weight is drawn, I
shivering in that eternal cold shadow. I
know not if it was will or destiny or
chance. But as I walked among the heads,
I struck my foot hard in the face of
one. Weeping, he chided them, "Why
trample me if you've not come to act the
revenge of Montiperi? Why do you molest
me?"
And I, my master, now wait here for me,
that I may clear up just one doubt about
him. Then you can make me hurry as you
will. My guide stood fast and I went on
to ask of him who still was cursing
bitter bitterly. Who are you that
rebukes another? So, and who are you who
go through antora striking the cheeks of
others? He replied, too roughly even if
you were alive.
I am alive and can be precious to you if
you want fame was my reply. For I can
set your name among my other notes.
and he to me, I want the contrary, so go
away and do not harass me. Your flattery
is useless in this valley. At that I
grabbed him by the scruff and said,
"You'll have to name yourself to me, or
else you won't have even one hair left
up here." And he to me, "Though you
should strip me bald, I should shall not
tell you who I am or show it, not if you
pound my head a thousand times." His
hairs were wound around my hand already,
and I had plucked from him more than one
tuft while he was barking, and his eyes
stared down when someone else cried out,
"What is it, Baka? Isn't the music of
your jaws enough for you without your
bark? What devils at you?"
And now I said, "You traitor bent on
evil. I do not need your talk, for I
shall carry true news of you, and that
will bring you shame." "Be off," he
answered. Tell them who you like, but
don't be silent if you make it back
about the one whose tongue was now so
quick. Here he laments the silver of the
Frenchmen. I saw you then can say him of
Derera down there where all the sinners
are kept cool.
And if you asked who else was there in
ice, one of the bacteria and beside you,
he had his skull sliced right through by
Florence. Johnny Del Soder, I believe,
lies there with Ganelon and Tabaldello.
He who unlocked Benza while it slept.
We had already taken leave of him when I
saw two shades frozen in one hole, so
that one once had served as the other's
cap. And just as he whose hungry choose
his bread, one sinner dug his teeth into
the other right at the place where
brainest joined to nape. No differently
had tidiest not the temples of Manalopus
out of indignation than this one chewed
the skull and other parts. Oh you who
show with such beastial sign your hatred
for the one on whom you feed tell me the
cause. I said we can agree that if you
quarrel with him is justified then
knowing who you are and what's this
what's his sin I shall repay you yet on
earth above if that with which I speak
does not dry up.
>> Okay. All right. So we are in the final
circle of hell and it's a completely
frozen lake where everyone is submerged
in a lake and just freezing. They can't
move. They can only feel pain and um
there are also divisions within this
lake and they're name they're given
different names and they are ranked
according to the what they betrayed.
Okay. So at the outer layer there's the
betrayal of family. So basically two
brothers who killed each other. Okay.
Betrayal of family.
Okay. Then as you go further down there
is the betrayal
of country. [snorts]
Okay. So the example is BA. And who is
Baka? FA is someone who
um fought for the Florentines with
Dante, but he was not loyal to the
Florentines. And at a battle, a crucial
battle between the Gves and the Gil
Gilibbeines, he betrayed the Gves by
cutting off the hand of the standard
bearer. Okay, the standard bearer, if
you know your uh medieval battles, the
standard bearer is essentially like
captain of the flag or the king in the
game of chess, right?
uh the Senate barrier is what gives uh
direction, hope and focus to the army.
So this caused the GS to lose a major
battle. Okay. And that's why um Baka is
being punished and Donnie recognizes him
and demands that he speak up. Baka is
like no I rather be forgotten. Okay. So
lower down is the betrayal of country.
Then you have the betrayal
of
um friends
and then you have the betrayal
of
guests. Okay. So again, the thing about
divine comedy is it's full of paradoxes.
And if you actually look at this, you
would think that it would be the
opposite, right? Like betrayal of guests
would be the least punished and the most
punished would be betrayal of family
because family is tied together by
blood. So what's going on here? Why
would Donnie construct
his
n circle of treachery in such a manner?
Okay. What's the criteria that he's
using to judge the sin? Uh, yes.
>> I think it's about how it reflects to
the universe. So, if you betray a
family, it only concerns yours, whereas
a guest can really concern anyone on
earth. Yes.
>> And so, it disrupts trust.
>> Yes. Thank you. Yes.
>> I think in the Middle East as well, like
in Iran or like in Israel, I guess, to
treat a guest, you have to put up the
best hospitality. It's because it's
stranger. I think it's underlying the
same principle.
>> Uh, Kong,
>> well, I think you have a great idea, but
I'm not sure if it was if that was the
case. I feel like friends would be a
smaller circle than country. And so
those two circles would be the opposite.
And so maybe we could work that into the
new theory.
>> You will, right? You choose because
because you don't choose your family.
You you might not even choose the
country you're born on, but you choose
your friends and you invite your guests.
>> Exactly. Yes.
>> I think I like the reflection idea and
it's about what is contrary to the
nature of the universe. And as humans
with bodies, we are guests. So he's
asking what would God really never do.
Of course, he would never betray these
other groups, but
they are all subsumed within the group
of guests under God. So it's really the
major violence against God is against
guests.
>> Okay. Great. Okay. Yeah. So I think
Evelyn's right. Okay. So to summarize,
it's the idea that um we have a
responsibility to protect love and the
imagination in the universe. Okay.
Without love, there can be no
imagination. Love is based on trust. So
the more trust you create in the
universe, the greater the capacity for
love in the universe. Therefore, the
greater capacity for imagination.
Um again the idea of free will where we
all have a choice whether or not to
enter in a contract right the idea of a
social contract we choose to enter a
social contract
and what's really important is to honor
those social contract. The thing about
family is you don't choose to enter in a
social contract. You're just stuck with
a family. Okay? You don't choose your
country. You're stuck with your country.
But you do choose your friends and you
do choose who to invite into your
household.
Okay? And and um also what's really
important is the idea of guests. Like
the iron law of most society is to treat
guests with hospitality. This is true
for most of human history, not just the
Middle East, okay? Anywhere in the
world. Okay? You don't really appreciate
this but at this time if a stranger
comes from far away you have an urgent
responsibility to treat him with the
most utmost respect. Okay nowadays
you're like oh immigrants let's kill
immigrants. No no no no immigration for
of most of human history was really rare
and was much common was just the
traveler right and so if you saw a
traveler you had to treat that person
with with utmost respect and
hospitality. And the reason why is well
if you kill that person then no one
could ever travel right? No one could
ever nobody ever explore. And um in in
the Greek mythology in the Greek society
what they believe that every guest could
potentially be a god in disguise. So to
kill a guest would be to upset the gods
themselves. Okay. And so um did did
sorry did you have a question or
comment?
>> Um yeah. So what's then even worse
probably is that if you're a guest you
um disrespect the host because that's
what Paris for example did when he was
he was a guest in Greece and then he
stole Helen or when the Greece were
basically guests in Troy and then they
destroyed Troy.
>> Yes, exactly. Yes. Um that's a really
special case. This is something I never
really thought about where the guest
purposefully uh betrays the host. Uh but
but that's a great question for us to
think about and this is something that
uh if Dante knew about he would
definitely put uh Paris in here as well.
Yeah, that that's a really great
comment. Um but does this make sense to
you guys? Okay, unless you have trust,
society cannot function at all. Right? I
mean, think about how um you like like
for example, the most bas basic thing is
you often set disputes, right? If
there's a war going on, you would invite
the opposing general for a dinner,
right? And like if you just kill the
general like there there could be no
reconciliation, there could be no no
mediation, right? So this idea of like
honoring guests, it's an iron law
throughout all human society. Okay, it's
true in China. It's true everywhere.
Right? And the reason why is that if you
didn't have this law, so society just
could not function. Okay? There could be
no basis for any contract. Okay? All
right. So that's what's going on here.
All right. Let's keep on going.
KTO 33.
That sinner raised his mouth from his
fierce meal. Then used the head that he
had ripped apart in back. He wiped his
lips upon its hair. Then he began, "You
want me to renew desparing pain that
presses at my heart even as I think back
before I speak. But if my words are seed
from which the fruit fruit is infamy for
this betrayer whom I gnaw, you'll see me
speak and weep at once. I don't know who
you are or in what may you've come down
here. And yet you surely seem for what I
hear to be Florentine. You're to know I
was Count Ugalino. And this one here,
Archbishop Rubiieri. And now I'll tell
you why I'm his neighbor. There's no
need to tell you that because of his
malicious tricks, I first was taken then
was killed since I had trusted him.
However, that which you cannot have
heard, that is the cruel death for me,
you now shall hear and know if he has
wronged me.
A narrow window in the eagle's tower,
which now through me is called the
hunger tower. A cage in which still
others will be locked, had through its
opening already showed me several moons.
When I dreamed that bad dream which rent
the curtain of the future for me, this
man appeared to me as lord and master.
He hunted down the wolf and its young
welps upon the mountain that prevents
the peons from seeing Luca. And with
lean and keen and practiced hounds he
sent up front before him wandi and
sismundi and the Frankie. But after a
brief course it seemed to me that both
the father and the sons were weary. I
seemed to see their flanks torn by sharp
fangs. When I awoke at daybreak I could
hear my sons who were together with me
there weeping within their sleep asking
for bread. You would be cruel indeed if
thinking what my heart foresaw. You
don't already grieve. And if you don't
weep now, when would you weep? They were
awake by now. The hour drew near at
which our food was usually brought. And
each, because of what he dreamed, was
anxious. Below I heard them nailing up
the door of that appalling tower without
a word. I looked into the faces of my
sons.
I did not weep. Within I turned to
stone, they wept. And my poor little
handsome said, "Father, you look so what
is wrong with you?" At that I shed no
tears and all day long and through the
night that followed did not answer until
another sun had touched the world. As
soon as a thin ray had made its way into
that sorry prison and I saw reflected in
four faces my own gaze. Out of my grief
I bit at both my hands. And they who
thought I'd done that out of hunger
immediately rose and told me, "Father,
it would be far less painful for us if
you ate of us. for you clothed us in
this sad flesh. It is for you to strip
it off.
Then I grew calm to keep them from more
sadness. Through that day, and the next
we all were silent, "Oh hard earth, why
did you not open up?" But after we had
reached the fourth day, God, throwing
himself outstretched down at my feet,
implored me, "Father, why do you not
help me?" And there he died. And just as
you see me, I saw the other three fall
one by one, between the fifth and the
sixth, at which now blind, now blind, I
started groping over each, and after
they were dead, I called them for two
days. Then fasting had more force than
grief.
>> Okay. All right. So the story is um at
this time in history, Count Yugalino is
one of the most famous Italians. He is a
great military strategist. uh of Pisa
and um eventually because he is so
ambitious, he's a very Makavedan figure
um he will change alliances always and
then he falls into alliance with the
archbishop who then betrays him in order
to obtain more power for himself. What
the archbishop does is that he locks him
and his and his children, his sons, into
a cell and force away the key. They
don't know this, but no one's coming to
them and giving them food. So they're
just starving to death. And the um urban
legend is that uh Count Ugandano
cannibis children in order to keep
himself alive.
Um first of all we discussed the idea of
symmetry in the in the vine comedy.
Okay. Do you guys know
uh and this this is like the second last
conto the penultimate kto right? What is
a penalty conto in Paradise that mirrors
this? Do you guys remember?
And and that's and that's what's uh
brilliant about Dante. He's always doing
symmetry in order to excite your
imagination. So here this is a father
cannibalizing his children. You guys
remember in the Panama Canal of Paradise
what the issue was there? what they were
talking about uh in uh the pandemic
candle of paradise basically paradise 32
what do we spend a lot of time
discussing
>> like the babies in heaven
>> yes do you see the symmetry here right
and we we back then Bernard was telling
Dante why is it that
in the seat of in the in the red rose
right beside God you have the greatest
uh matriarchs in history, Eve, Mary, and
Rachel and Rof, but you also had babies.
And Don is like, "Wait a minute. I
thought Virgil told me babies were all
in limbo." And but you had these babies
and we we decided that it was because of
the uh unconditional love of parents,
right? If a baby died and if a parent
committed himself to unconditional love,
praying to God, commit to good works,
that effort would allow the child to
ascend to the imperium. And here we have
the complete opposite, right? It's an
opposite. It's it's it's an inverse
where the father is cannibalizing his
sons in order to um survive. Okay. Okay.
So that's the beauty of the divine
comedy. You'll find the the symmetry
everywhere. Okay. All right.
So, um
what is going on here? Why is uh
Countino
biting on the archbishop and why are
they forcing in place and why is this
happening for all eternity? [snorts]
I guess
>> I guess in the simple sense he's just
trying to exact an appropriate revenge
and that this desire which is still
present in hell will just continue
forever.
>> Why are they in a frozen lake?
>> Because they have no imagination to move
them towards anything other than what
they desire.
>> Uh yes.
>> Could it be that they've thrown away
their free will because there's
I find the line. But he's basically
asking, you know, father, why don't you
help me? Implying that he's looking for
that external help rather than earlier
on we spoke about how you can through
your own free will help yourself.
>> Yes. Any other comments or thoughts?
Yes.
>> And also like betrayal kind of freezes
your relationship with the others and
then like the others will also like no
longer trust anyone because of these
sorts of like betrayal. Yes. So like you
are also freeze in a lake yourself after
you betray the others.
>> Yes. Exactly.
Any anymore?
>> Okay. Yeah. Exactly. Right. They're in a
frozen lake. These are frozen literally
in time. Right. All they remember is the
betrayal and they're first for revenge,
the hatred. Okay. And the punishment is
apt because just as um the archbishop
forced the count to betray his sons and
cannibalize his sons, now the count is
cannibalizing uh the archbishop, but
it's all futile because they're all in
hell. Uh but he doesn't care because
he's stuck in that moment. Okay? He's
not actually consider considering the
absurdity of the situation. He's just
stuck in that in that moment. And that's
the idea of frozen lake. Okay? That's
why hell at the very bottom everyone
everyone is a frozen lake because the
treachery has frozen them in that moment
of treachery and they can never escape
out of it and they they lack the
capacity to have free will to have the
love imagination to think beyond this
moment of of betrayal. All they focus on
is how do I get back at at this person
for the betrayal. Okay. And that's why
uh betrayal is the worst punishment
because the universe moves and betrayal
treachery
freezes the universe in place. Okay, it
reduces the capacity for imagination.
Okay, does that make sense? Great. All
right, let's keep on uh
going. This is the very last.
Oh yeah, sorry. Sorry. Keep on going.
We're not finished this yet.
>> Um line 76. When he had spoken this with
eyes of again he gripped the sad skull
in his teeth which like a dogs were
strong down to the bone. Aisa you the
scandal of the peoples of that fair land
where sea is heard because your
neighbors are so slow to punish you. May
then Capra and Gorgona move and build a
hedge across the Arno's mouth so that
you may drown every soul in you. For if
Count Ugalino was reputed to have
betrayed your fortresses, there was no
need to have his sons endure such
torment. Oh thieves renewed, their years
were innocent and young. Brigata Ubuchi
and the other two my song has named
above. We passed beyond where frozen
water wraps a rugged covering still
other sinners who were not who were not
bent but flat upon their backs. So Dante
is moved by the story and he's upset
about what? What about the story really
upsets him and
makes him very confused? Yes.
>> That Countina was forced to sin and why
well why would someone be punished in
exactly the same way if they didn't
instigate the betrayal?
Okay. So, um he thinks that Count Ulano
got what he deserved because he did
betray Pisa and the people the pie were
angry at this. Okay. But there's a
problem here. Yes.
>> I think maybe the problem is that uh Cal
Ugalino's sons were actually tortured in
the same way.
>> Yeah. Why the sons in prison? The sons
did nothing wrong. First of all, why why
the sons in prison?
I believe it's to torture Count Ugalino,
but I don't understand why they were
subject to the same torture as Ugalino
did.
>> Okay. Yeah. But but but but this is just
a historical question, right? Why are
children being punished along with the
fathers? Yes.
>> Presumably, they would grow up and try
and exact vengeance in the
>> Exactly. Right. This is true for most
cultures at this time. You if you kill
the father, you have to kill the sons as
well because now now the sons are
morally obligated to avenge the father.
Okay. And so Don is like saying this is
unjust.
Okay. And what what he's saying is like
we have to remember we have to have
faith that there are higher laws of
justice that govern us and to punish the
sons with a father. Yes, I understand
the logic. I understand that it's
necessary because you want to avoid
wars, right? Because at this time in
history, family feuds are a real thing.
Okay. But he says, "I understand all
this, but it's still unjust."
Okay? And again, at this time in
history, it's pretty revolutionary.
You guys know the story of Romeo and
Juliet, right? Well, it's this time,
okay? The Monu and the Capulates, it is
this time, these Italians city states in
Verona, right? These feuds, these family
feuds that go go on for generations,
okay? It is it is this time in history.
Okay. Uh let's keep on going.
Lie 94. Their very weeping there won't
let them weep. And grief that finds a
barrier in their eyes turns inward to
increase their agony because their first
tears freeze into a cluster and like a
crystal visor fill up all the hollow
that is underneath the eyebrow. And
though because of cold my every sense
had left its dwelling in my face, just
as a callous has no feeling, nonetheless
I seem to feel some wind now. And I
said, "My master, who has set this gust
in motion? For isn't every vapor
quenched down here?" And he to me, "You
soon shall be where your own eye will
answer that when you shall see the
reason why this wind blasts from above."
And one of those sad sinners in the cold
crust cried to us, "Oh souls who are so
cruel that this last place has been
assigned to you, take off the hard veils
from my face so that I can release the
suffering that fills my heart before
lament free presses again.
to which I answered, "If you'd have me
help you, then tell me who you are. If I
don't free you, may I go to the bottom
of the ice?" He answered, "Then I'm Fro
Elberiggo, the one who tended fruits in
a bad garden, and here my figs have been
repaid with dates." But then I said,
"Are you already dead?" And he to me, "I
have no knowledge of my body's fate
within the world above, for pollia
has this privilege. Quite frequently the
soul falls here before it has been
thrusted away by a tropos. And that you
may with much more willingness scrape
these glazed tears from off my face.
Know this. As soon as any soul becomes a
traitor, as I was, then a demon takes
its body away and keeps that body in its
power until its years have run their
course completely.
The soul falls headlong down into the
sistern and up above. Perhaps there
still appears the body of the shade that
winters here behind me. You must know
him if you've just come down. He is Sir
Broncadoria. For many years he has been
thus pent up. I said to him, I think
that you deceive me, for Bronadoria is
not yet dead. He eats and drinks and
sleeps and puts on clothes. There in the
mala bronke ditch above, where sticky
pitch boils up, Mikalli Zankke had not
had still not come. He said to me, when
this one together with a kinsman who had
done the treachery together with him,
left a devil in hisstead instead his
body.
But now reach out your hand, open my
eyes, and yet I did not open them for
him, and it was courtesy to show him
rudeness. Ah, Genoez, a people strange
to every constraint of custom, full of
all corruption. Why have you not been
driven from the world? For with the
foulest spirit of Rammania I found one
of you such that for his acts in soul he
bathed already in koshittas and up above
appears alive in body.
>> Okay. So we have met the worst
offenders. Okay. These are people who
betrayed their guest. They invite their
guests to dinner and now they're
protected by the laws of hospitality.
Right? But they don't care. They betray
their guest. And the moment they do
that, what happens is they their sin is
so bad they they automatically their
souls are taken down to the ninth
circle.
They are trapped in the frozen lake and
a demon takes possession of their body.
Okay. And uh the example here is Brana
Doria. Um and Donnie actually knows this
person and Donnie knows this person is
alive and he's saying that now a demon
took over his body. Okay. So here's a
question for you.
Do you think demonic possession or
angelic possession is it real?
Any thoughts? Any comments? And again
there are no right answers, but I'm I'm
curious as to what you think. Yes. Well,
if you grow up in Southeast Asia, in
Malaysia or Singapore, there's udu magic
as we all know. Um, so then or in
Africa, like if you grow up in these
regions of the world, it's impossible
for you to conceive that a ghost
[clears throat] or demon cannot take
possession of a human being because you
see it all the time.
>> Wow.
>> Not all the time like
common sense.
>> Elaborate on this because why is it that
like in these societies you see ghosts
and demons, but we don't? Uh
>> okay
>> I recently moved back [laughter]
>> but okay so um
because I think it's because of the
religion of the local people this kind
of m magical practices is a lot
especially Malays right like uh there's
a thing like if you dig out that man's
body and you take some liquid from his
jar and you can make it into love potion
the most common one everybody knows in
Malaysia it's a thing okay like yeah and
so like yeah so then then you can make
the men fall in love with you or women
and that's common practice and then you
can do a lot of these.
>> How does dematic possession work?
Um,
so in Udu is like you do this spell and
then you have this doll and then you
stab it, right? And then like in in
Malaysia or you know there there are a
lot like you you ask this guy to come to
your house, you pay him and then to
curse that guy and then that
yeah
>> there's a whole they have their own.
>> So so what you're saying is do do you
know about this? I don't know about this
but but go ahead
>> from Catholic worldview um
>> there is Lydia in the Bible or whoever I
forgot the lady's name but like there
are people who are possessed by demons
and Jesus had to cast it down but like
go to the pigs and and the pigs drawn
themselves so in Bible it's very common
in Malaysia it's very common and yeah
Africa
>> actually speaking of um my husband and I
have recently watched a Tucker Carlson
podcast with um a priest who is an
exorcist,
>> right?
>> And um actually
um you know it's it's an you know in in
many cultures it's actually an ongoing
thing. Um, and even in China, um, I I've
heard that, for example, um, in the
northeast there are animal spirits. And
also growing up in Hong Kong, um, under
certain bridges, there are people doing
voodoo stuff. Um, you can pay someone
to, um, let's say stab a pin into a doll
or hit someone, hit someone's effigy.
>> Okay. Um,
>> so, so, so voodoo is across cultures
basically.
>> Yeah. If you look at University of Hong
Kong, there's a huge tomb. Okay. In the
library. Have you have you been to
University of Hong Kong?
>> I have. I I don't but I don't know about
this.
>> Yeah. Like if you think out of all like
Hong Kong is such a epitome, you know,
of all these practices, fun and all
that. But if you go to University of
Hong Kong, there's a limb built for his
wife and it's the the library look like
a tomb literally to calm her spirit. So
there's a lot of this kind of practices
where people believe that.
>> So you guys believe in this stuff. I'm
saying like if you don't believe in this
stuff, what are your objections to it?
>> Who who is like this can't possibly
exist? Yes.
>> I think that when someone commits a sin
that seems to have a character that is
beyond their normal character, that
there's a life force inside of the sin,
it's easy and tempting to assume that
there is a a vortex of energy that
creates consciousness that is separate
from their own that has come into them.
M
>> but it just strikes me that this is
cope. This is people who really don't
want to accept that maybe someone they
know their friend or their family could
do a sin that was so out of character.
>> Okay. All right. That's very
interesting. Okay. Let let me ask you
this question. Okay. Did do we have a
let me ask you this question. Um does
anyone want to comment on how he or she
has changed after reading Divine Comedy?
like we've spent the past week reading
Divine Comedy. We still have a few more
days left, but has does anyone want to
reflect on how he or she has changed
after encountering Divine Comedy for the
first time after reading it, after
thinking about it? Do you think you've
changed as a person? Do you think? Yes.
>> Uh I don't believe that it can change
people because before that maybe people
thought, "Oh, I just cheat. I do
whatever I can. nobody will you know get
to know more about me and I just hide
myself. So but after uh you know divine
comedy maybe some people saying can have
confessions maybe some people think
they're guilty right because
>> okay
>> I'm not asking this as an thought
experiment I'm just asking like have you
personally
felt different after reading the vine
comedy?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Can you explain this? H it's hard to put
it into words but um for me um
especially after Paradisio
uh as well as in like as we go through
line by line the divine comedy um you
you you
you can't it's for me I feel like it's
alluding to a larger truth um and it's a
it's it's making me more open to the
fact that there are things beyond this
universe that I don't really understand
[snorts] because I I'm an a scientist
engineer by training um I and then later
on went into business right so I I um
it's it's it's quite you know framework
changing for me I don't know how to put
>> Have you um felt any physical changes to
your body
>> like the first night um kind of like the
first night I think I I I I mentioned
this to some of our classmates like um
um I find I find it hard to sleep
actually the first few nights um even
paradigio right um supposedly this good
thing but I I I found it hard to
rest uh as per my usual routine. Um
mainly because I find all these
imageries and all these things kind of
kicking off thoughts in myself, right?
Wondering about the nature of good and
you know
>> so so these visions were appearing
before you and you're trying to wrestle
with these visions.
>> Okay, that's interesting.
>> Similar to in hell, right? like like
like just just you know um we you
mentioned something about I'm trying to
square a circle, right? like uh the fact
that there's Muhammad in there and there
is um um um uh things about sodomy and
homosexuality and like I I find myself
trying to answer questions that weren't
there before and like coming up with oh
should I go talk to different people I
know who are
>> and and [clears throat] and um so I
don't know I don't I I I do think there
is I just don't know how to you know
>> okay yes
feel like there's way more awareness
awareness and consciousness about uh the
people we meet, the people we love and
the people who loved us and I feel like
first of all it's very tiring so every
time like even though we have four hours
four hours of class I feel like super
tired at the end often take a nap and
also I felt in dreams I thought of
people that I I forgot and so you
rethink
um about certain moments of your life
and how it's linked to of wow
especially.
>> Well, that's beautiful. Thank you so
much. So, you're expanding your
consciousness, your connection to the
cosmos,
right? Okay. Anyone else have
this will sound extremely strange, but a
lot of my lymph nodes started draining
when I really studied the divine comedy.
I think because my nervous system was
really relaxing and genuinely a lot of
like waste product from my body was
being expelled.
>> Wow. Okay. Okay. So, you felt some
physical changes.
Okay. Anyone else? Yes.
>> Yeah. Kind of I kind of felt the same
cuz I dream like a lot more frequently
for these few days. And also like I kind
of agree what with what both of them
said. I feel like I kind of reexamine my
connection and relationship with the
others. And then I kind of see like how
it is so important to me that I have to
cherish them. And also like at the same
time I was kind of like an atheist
before reading the Divine Comedy. Now I
cannot say that I entirely believe that
God exists but I feel like I'm kind of
like re-examining what I used to
believe.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Great. Thank you so much. Any other
uh Yes.
>> Uh similar to the classmates I think uh
dream dreams have been a bit different.
Yes.
>> In the last few weeks. Uh like I
remember on the first day we read the
divine comedy I had like quite a vivid
nightmare and I don't really have
nightmares very often.
>> The only way I can try and understand it
I think is usually in uh day-to-day life
we don't really think about morality
very much and its effect on us or
others. So we're kind of
numbed. But obviously in the last uh
week or so, yeah, it's every day think
yeah thinking about things we don't
usually think about and maybe raising
the consciousness.
>> Okay, let me ask you this. Has anyone
tried psychedelics in this class?
>> Uh yes. Can you talk about your psych
psychedelic experience?
>> First of all, what did you try?
>> Psychedelic mushrooms.
>> Okay. So,
>> so a couple of times last year. So it
wasn't like extreme but still like
enough to feel like some extra forces.
So it's really about uh same thing like
social awareness. So you feel like
positive negative energy when you like
you feel happy and loved close to your
friends and you feel really insecure in
some environment that's like negative.
>> So so so I I want to confirm this. Okay.
Yours like experience is very similar to
you reading the vine comedy. It could be
but like it's it's really hard to
compare and I think like you can't reach
this level of awareness just by reading
or meditation like it's really like
physical uh visual and about love like
it's really strong and you can't like
there's a 100% chance you feel something
with this experience whereas by reading
it's maybe like couple percent but a bit
a bit but it's hard to compare it like
>> I actually would differ on that because
Um I've also done transcendental
meditation when I was a child and um I
had a similar experience with Jay uh
which is one night um I had a vision. I
haven't had a vision for a long time
since I was younger. So um and I've done
other mindopening things. So um I I
would I would say they're different in
every way. It's just that um there's
something pre precious or different
about the reading and going through this
journey.
>> Yeah. So, so my my argument would be
well that's because you have not fully
read the B comedy, right? We're just
scratching the surface. If you really
commit to it, maybe it be similar but
but but did you want to share your
experience? Yeah, I have to agree with
um against you or
the end point of a lot of like mushroom
trips maybe less for LSD is basically
the message of this.
>> Yes.
>> Where like
>> imagine if this is crystal clear your
own revelations at the end of a trip are
like slight flaws in a crystal. So it's
your personality rewriting the truth
that is contained here. And so it's very
strange that when you really try to
unlock your brain, this is the kind of
message that you end up.
>> This is like really strange. Yeah. Let
me ask you guys, let me ask you another
question. Has anyone had an intense
religious experience? Okay. Yes. Can you
can you explain to us your intense
religious experience
just in your life? Like you've gone to
church.
>> Yeah. Yeah. That was definitely one um
that's what made me actually converted
to Christianity. So I always so after I
went to Malaysia when I was 12, uh I
lived in a pastor's family and just like
two years after that I wasn't convinced
about Christianity. I was oh that's
cool. Bible stories are awesome. And
then there was one month where I had
nightmares every night where I had this
um
visits from hell basically and I'm
afraid to go to bed every night because
I know what's waiting for me in my
dreams. And I there was nothing
traumatic happening in my life. There
was no exam stress. There was no, you
know, and then I was just terrified. And
then my pastor, uh, dad and mom were
like, "Well, read the Bible verse out
loud in your room and recite it." And
that was the only night I didn't have
nightmare. And the girl next to me, poor
thing. She had a nightmare. And that was
really gruesome. She said, "Did you left
your room and come to my room now?" I'm
like, "I'm so sorry. Maybe I shouldn't
have read the Bible out loud. My
[laughter] bad." And then so that kind
of really convinced me of like hell
existed and like so I had to scream the
name of Jesus to get out of that
nightmare. And then from that whole
month of torture is over like if anybody
swear to me oh there's no God in the
room like you like come to my life
be in that month and then like explain
to me why is there all these crazy
things that just make me Yeah. not being
able to not believe there's no spiritual
world.
>> So let me confirm what you're saying.
You're you're you're in Malaysia and
there's a lot of voodoo magic in
Malaysia. So, it's possible there are
lots of these spirits roaming around.
>> Yeah.
>> And these spirits were literally like
knocking your door. But once you um
found some incantations like you know
some Bible verses, it changed your
energy field as though to create a force
field around you
>> protection.
That's went to the next girl's room and
she was like, "Anna, I never had a
nightmare ever in my life." But last
night you did have the nightmare I do
now. I'm so sorry baby. You know the
ghost left me and went to your room.
Sorry.
>> Okay. So then the question then is why
does this happen? Why is it like when
you read the divine comedy you have
these dreams and why is it like even
your body physically changes? Why? Yes.
>> I could see this as a priming. So in
psychology there's something called
priming where you put something into
your mind.
>> And so to have these words by reading
about love, will and hope.
>> Um it like just so you have these words
and so in every interaction you have you
think of this and so it really changed
what you're talking because like if you
just read about love and then you're
talking to your mother then obviously
you're going to think about this. And so
this is how it changes like the aspect
about priming, putting words into your
head and then always associating with
with this.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Okay. This is what a
psychologist would tell you. It's all
priming, right? Because they've done
experiments where uh if you if in the
morning what you do is you get some
sunlight and you put on some really nice
music, you feel better about yourself
and you have a nicer day. Whereas if you
um don't go outside and you put on some
really sad music, you're gonna have a
really bad day. Okay. So, a lot of a lot
of it is priming a lot of its
self-perception. Okay. Yes.
>> Um I loved having that conversation with
her. Um we actually had a previous
conversation in the elevator which
probably primed our later comment about
music. But actually when I have uh when
I had the recent vision, it reminded me
of previous visions where it felt like a
resonance with the universe where I
could see things in
just a different dimension
um and different colors. And it's the
resonance with the rest of the universe
that doesn't happen all the time for a
lot of reasons,
>> but um it's resonance, harmony, that
concordance that kind of comes when
there's a really powerful work of art or
mind opening that's happening.
>> Okay. Yes. Okay. I I understand that.
But I'm trying to figure out the
psychedelic experience then. Explain to
me how psychedelics work then. You you
you explain how divine comedy works.
It's priming. Yes. But how psychedelics?
>> So first of all like psychedelics what's
different is that there's like 100%
chance that it will change you like you
will feel different. Uh so it's often
seen as a trip where like you basically
lose your consciousness and everything
you know or knew and it basically makes
you way more close to nature where you
forget the conception of like
technology, money, uh possession. And so
during a couple of hours between like 4
to 8 hours you just feel basically like
an animal where you rethink everything.
You you basically like also you can't
use your phone, right? Because like it's
so not human that it changes you.
>> But no, I'm trying to figure out the
neurological mechanism that allows for
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. But just just just
just one one last question. Okay. What's
a neurological mechanism? You've
explained priming. How do you explain
psychedelics?
>> Um I think it's like some molecule like
psyocybin or like something.
>> Okay. Yes.
>> I don't know. I think you're referring
to um silosin which is the thing that
breaks down from the mushrooms. But I
think it all comes down to a molecule I
think called tryptoamine which so
basically in your brain there's a
molecule that constrains your
perception. So imagine your eyes are
seeing fractals all the time and that
your brain is basically organizing the
sense data from those fractals into
reality. And then if you boost a certain
chemical a lot, you start to see the
fractalss that your brain is using to
perceive reality. And this happens
internally as well for your mind and
being.
>> So if I extrapolate on what you're
saying, you're saying that reality
itself is much more complex, much more
vibrant, much more colorful than we
could ever imagine.
>> Way way more.
>> But and then these what these do is they
basically uh cancel out your filter so
you see more of reality,
>> right? But but that's all that's saying
is like maybe demons and angels actually
do exist, right? Is that is I mean is
that the possibility?
>> I don't want to say 100% but you get
that sense.
>> And so possession is also possible,
right? Because what's because the idea
is they exist. They're floating around
us and um they you depending on your
mood, depending on your state of mind,
they can come into you. they can leave
you, right? Is that a possibility?
Okay, so let me ask you this really
weird question.
Do any of you while we in divine comedy,
do you feel intuitely as though
Dante
has entered you?
Do you think at some level Dante has
taken possession of you?
Uh uh sorry so sorry so sorry so sorry
so sorry so sorry so sorry so sorry so
sorry so sorry so sorry so sorry uh you
first and then
>> yeah yeah yeah definitely because uh I I
think I don't know why you come here to
this classroom but I do because I think
I just been excelled you know I just uh
you know uh I don't know just I think
I'm out of the social system right now
just because maybe uh I do my part-time
job I don't just always like other
people to to go to work all the day long
so maybe uh that make me feel like like
Dante you know I I just being driven
away Right. I'm saying I'm like
physically donating. Yeah. Yeah. Yes.
>> I think so. But I'm lucky because I
studied the Anid when I was 18 in Latin.
Just luckily.
>> Yes.
>> And I for some reason have my own
biatric in my real life like a girl who
I'm super in love with who is now dating
somebody who knows lots about wine.
>> Yes.
>> So in a strange sense this is I do feel
him inside me in that sense.
>> Okay. and and and h and how do you how
do you feel it? H how how do you know
he's inside you?
>> Because there seems to be an energy
directing me to be kinder to strangers
and to spread more love that feels very
physical because of how much power and
energy it has, but that I've never been
able to conjure in myself just from a
desire to be good.
>> But how do you know it's Dante not an
angel or another spiritual being? like
like like what differentiates this from
>> well I don't want to presume I think
it's dangerous to think that an angel
can come into you um and
>> but you're presuming Dante who's dead
can come into you right
>> well through his work
>> yes
>> I just don't want to think that an angel
has come into me because it's a very
slippery slope about what you might do
then
>> okay yeah so so that's what great art is
great art um becomes part of the
universal consciousness and by reading
it um if you read it well I'm not saying
if you read it like you know what the
way we're reading but I'm saying like if
you read it over years and years and you
continue have these visions and you
continue have these spiritual
experiences and you continue to practice
divine comedy in your life then
eventually Don is going to take
possession of you and he's going to
reveal things to you that were once
unimaginable to you before and it's very
similar to a religious experience. It's
very similar to psychedelic experience.
Yes.
>> Actually, professor, I would really
appreciate it if you could share the
changes that you experienced yourself as
well cuz like if we went through like
the divine comedy within a week and then
we all experienced some changes to a
certain extent and then you spent four
years on it, I think you definitely
experienced a lot more than we did.
>> Okay. So, I'll tell you some of my
changes. Okay. Um, first of all, what's
really obvious to me is I feel a lot
lighter, like physically a lot lighter,
as though I am almost like floating in
the air. Okay? Because, you know, um,
when you're in China, like every day
it's a pain in the ass, right? Because,
you know, like when you're walking the
streets, there's scooters flying around.
Okay? when you go to the restaurant,
often the food is going to be, you know,
it's going to give you food poisoning.
Okay. Um, and then to and then you might
get in an argument with someone with
someone on, you know, it's it's a very
common thing in China. So it's and like
when when that happens what I feel is
really heavy you know like just my blood
boiling and just like you know like pure
hatred and just pure anger, right? Just
like just really I'm just really
annoyed. Okay, because I love walking
and Beijing is not a walking city and it
annoys me. I I feel trapped. I I feel
like I can't go outside because if I go
outside, a scooter might bump into me
and I I'll get angry and and all that.
Okay. So, uh but when I read the Divine
Comedy, all that dissipates, right? And
that anger, those memories for the
reason they just float away and then I
feel I floating upwards. Okay, that's
one really obvious thing that I noticed.
Okay. But but but again, it's something
that and I think it's because I've been
reading Divine Comedy for a long time
and I understand it pretty well. Okay.
But so I'm saying like if you do read
the Divine Comedy over time, I'm pretty
sure you will feel the same thing where
you feel yourself lighter. It's almost
like you're lifting yourself up to the
heavens. It's almost like you can
actually access the heavens yourself.
Okay, that's that's one.
Second thing is that um I feel much more
creative. I feel much more imaginative.
Right? So when you in this class when
when I teach, you can see I teach with
imagination,
right? I'm going to propose ideas to
you. I'm going to propose situations to
you that are really imaginative. And I
think it's because as I am teaching, as
I'm reading Divine Comedy, I have a
cosmic connection with Dante. Um, and
Dante in the universe, it's feeding me
visions. It's feeding me ideas. The
difference between you guys and me is
you've just started. So these visions
are involuntary, meaning like they come
to you and you don't actually know what
to make of them. But if you practice
this for a long time like I have, you're
able to control these visions. You
basically say, I need this vision in
order to teach this.
Well, and the vision comes to you
automatically. Okay, I know it sounds
weird, but I have no idea what I'm
teaching, what I will teach. Okay, and
then on the cab right here, I know.
Okay, I know what I want to focus on. I
know what I want what I want to teach.
It's all
it's all very uh inspirational. Okay,
that's second thing. The third thing is
like when you actually read Dante a lot,
you feel a profound sense of purpose and
mission which is like my responsibility
is to share Dante with the world to
change the world for the better. You
feel as though if I really
uh I I have a special gift for
understanding tal for understanding
Dante and I have a mission to spread
this and and how do I know because I
think Dante is smiling at me from the
heavens. He's smiling at me and he's
like um you're spreading my message of
love and uh thank you so much. So, you
feel a deep sense of mission, but you
also feel a deep sense of gratitude,
uh, purpose, responsibility, and again,
but but like the ultimate sensation, and
I'm not sure if you guys ever had this,
is you feel really light. You feel as
though you're flying, you know, and you
feel as though you're ascending upwards.
It's almost like transcendence. Okay.
Transcendent. You're being transcendent
when you read Divine Comedy. Uh, yes.
Psych psychedelics. I totally agree with
the first two, but I think it still has
a lack of will and purpose at the end.
So, you do feel like elevated. You care
less about small things about, oh, I'm
late or oh, I like I don't have enough
money or something like it really
doesn't matter at all. You're connected
to a way higher purpose.
>> Yes.
>> Um, so you do feel lighter and creative
and you can direct your creativeness
into uh for example me as a student
learning. So you find new ways of
learning and way more efficiently. Uh
but we do like the actually um motion to
actually do things and yeah it's really
comparable.
>> Yeah, that's really interesting. Thank
you for that. Any more uh questions
before we continue?
>> Okay. All right. Uh let's Okay. So we
are going now to the ultimate KTO of
Inferno like the last KTO. Okay. But
before we do that, I want us to use our
imagination.
Okay? So, imagine we're we're we're in
Hollywood and writing this movie and we
we have the script already and now we
just have to figure out the ending,
right? And the ending of course is we
meet Lucifer.
We meet Satan. This is the ending of
Infernal. Okay. So, I want to use our
imagination and ask ourselves if we are
writing this movie. Okay. Uh first of
all, how would we
describe Lucifer? What is Lucifer? And
like how would we set the scene for the
ending? Okay. And again, this is the
ending,
right? So, any suggestions?
Come on. Let's let's be creative. Let's
channel Dante.
Uh yes.
Well,
look, I know we've read the ending, but
I'm just saying like, you know, let's
use our imagination. Pretend we have
not. Okay. Yes.
>> Well, our initial big question is, is he
tempting still or is he pitiful?
>> Exactly. Okay. So, the big question is
temptation because that is what Satan
does, right? He is going to meet Dante
and say to Dante, I know you're going to
meet you want to meet se meet, but let
me tempt you with other things, right?
Let me give you beautiful woman. Let me
give you riches. Let me give you a world
of kingdom. Right? That's the most
obvious thing you can do. Right?
Temptation. Just as Satan tempted Jesus
in the desert, Satan will now tempt
Dante in hell. Okay. So, that's obvious.
What What were some other things?
Uh yeah. Yes. Maybe try to sign a
contract because devil and the demon
they always want to sign contract with
make deal
>> a contract right
for your soul right and and this is the
plot of course for false and this is a
very common thing uh yes
well we have to show him tethered in
some way where he is selling a path
upwards to all the people he's giving
deals to so but we know God cast him out
of heaven forever. So his desire is to
get back there. He's caused mischief on
earth. So we need to show him if it was
a Hollywood movie in some way tied to
where he is in a way that he can never
escape.
>> Um can you describe his appearance for
us
>> in the poem or in
>> No, no, no, no. I I we know the what we
know the poem. Okay. But I'm saying like
if this were a Hollywood movie, right?
What what how would he look like who
would you cast to play Satan in this
movie? Uh
>> an AI character.
most handsome person possible as decreed
by a
>> I think handsome, right? Like like I
like I think like really good-looking.
Okay. Like maybe Brad Pit or Tom Cruz at
their prime. Okay. Like really hot,
really good-looking. Okay. Because
that's part of the temptation, right? So
beautiful. And you know in the Bible,
not in the Bible, like like Christianity
believes that Lucifer was a beautiful
angel, right? The most beautiful of all
the angels. So he has to be beautiful,
right? And he has to be like
um like really handsome and almost like
a prince, right? Okay. Any other ideas
for how how this will play out? Yes.
>> Like to what extent we can relate with
him? Like can we understand how he got
himself there or do we just see him very
>> This is really good. Yes. Sympathy.
Right. So Lucifer is going to tell us a
story of how [snorts]
he was betrayed by God, right? You think
I'm the betrayer, but God betrayed me.
And this becomes a plot line for
Paradise Lost. But but yeah, no, um we
have to sympathize with uh Satan because
it's not just tempting Dante, he has to
tempt us as well. He has to seduce us
with his um with his story. Yes.
Anything else?
one I would imagine him as a shape
shifter
>> because well and it's part of temptation
because um you kind of become whoever is
the object of someone's desire.
>> Yeah. Well, I would say he's a poet,
right? Because that's what a poet is. A
poet is a chameleon. Okay. A poet is
always shifting words to please you.
Okay. Lyrical. So when he speaks, it is
the most beautiful poetry in Divine
Comedy. It's lyrical. That's poetry and
he's a chameleon. Yes. Thank you. Anyone
else?
>> Yes.
>> Like very cunning or like lying like a
snake. So like how the temptation
happens in the garden of Eden. It will
be like did God really say this or like
actually word by word he didn't really
say that? And then kind of debates with
you and makes you kind of believe. He
has to be he has to be like he has to
provide logical syllogisms right
>> he has to convince you
>> yes okay he will be very convincing
right he'll use logic just as you know
in paradise laws where Satan convinced
Eve right it was a very logical speech
>> okay anyone else
I'd read Paradise Lost before I read
Inferno and so I was expecting it's like
a paradigm shift or the Germans would
call a gestalt shift. The gestalt shift
where like my entire world war worldview
changed because of um how Satan had had
expressed his point of view and so it
goes beyond sympathy to empathy um for
him and I expect him to to use that
persuasively. So yeah something beyond
>> temptation would be persuasive and
lawyerly. Yes. Yes. Like uh so every
argument that I would have this is
brother's carameliz every argument that
I would have would be steelmanned by him
and then broken down by him.
>> That's right. So not only do we have to
sympathize with him, we have to be like
feel that we are like him. Yes. Exactly.
Yes.
>> It makes me think about CS Lewis's uh
screw type letters. I think it was
basically written about a uncle demon
who is trying to teach his young uh
nephew demon to seduce people. So it was
all kinds of lectures from demons. So
these letters to teach him how to seduce
men and be like so it's really fun. So
that whole book was written in a demon's
perspective
>> which is very fun. But [clears throat]
it's about Yeah. All of these mentioned
above deception.
>> Where's Virgil in this movie? What
happens to Virgil? Right. Because they
went on this long journey together. What
happens to Virgil?
Any any any What would you do with
Virgil in this character? You know that
Dante's being tempted, right? And Dante
represents us and we know what Satan's
doing, but what's Virgil doing doing?
>> I mean, I guess if it was a movie, he'd
be transition to like a location where
he would quit he would be watching over
Dante but not involved in this scene at
all.
>> Yeah. Yeah. You I think the first thing
is that um Virgil would be trapped,
right? Or he would be frozen,
right? he'd be frozen and Satan would
use Virgil as a bargaining chip and
says, "Listen, your friend now is
frozen. If you love him, let's make a
deal, right?" So, you can almost see the
scene where Virgil and Dante come in and
the first thing that happens is that
Satan just snaps his finger and Virgil
is frozen in place. Cannot move, cannot
speak, and Dante is now terrified.
Right? And now Satan will begin his
temptation, tell his story, elicit
sympathy, then use his logic to convince
us that no actually the way we
understood the universe is wrong. God is
evil, Satan is good. That's why there's
this rebellion. Um
this basically helps plot Paradise Lost.
Okay. But but yeah. Um yes.
>> Um
I think he'd also inspire fear.
>> Yes. Right. Um,
>> he has to inspire fear and anxiety.
>> Mhm.
>> Right.
>> In the beginning, but then he wants you
to love him.
>> Does that make sense? Maybe in the
beginning he want fear and anxiety, but
then Yes.
>> He would also try to cause distrust
between maybe him and Virgil.
>> That's interesting. Yes. Okay.
>> So, because Virgil is his best friend up
to this point, and if he causes distrust
between them and it makes him
>> that is great. Yes. So maybe not freeze
Virgil, but um change Virgil and and
show um certain things, certain
flashbacks between Virgil and Donna that
show that Virgil is not a reliable
character. And there's quite a few of
these scenes. Yes.
>> Makes me think about like Harry Potter
where it's like kind of make you lose
all hope or despair or like kind of
breaks down of your fundamental belief
of the world. Yes. And then where like
the Harry Potter has to say expand no
Patronas to expel all these darkness and
despair in your life. So it's kind of
the similar.
>> Yes. Okay. Okay. So this is all great.
Okay. And like um this is what a
Hollywood movie would look like. This is
what most people would be right. Okay.
And guess what? We are completely and
utterly wrong. Okay. None of this
happens. In fact, the complete opposite
happens. Okay. [laughter]
All right. This is what's shocking about
the mind comedy. Um so we're going to
read we'll now read the last KTO again
this is what we should expect to happen
this is what most people would write in
fact a lot of people have written this
in in uh in literature got GA with false
Milton Paradise Lost you have Philip
Pullman who wrote his Dark Materials
trilogy um but that's how it happens
okay so let's read count 34 and we're
trying to figure out why
uh this does not happen.
>> Okay. KTO 34
Vexil Refer
toward us and therefore keep your eyes
ahead. My master said to see if you can
spy him.
>> Okay. So, they're now going to meet
Satan and or Lucifer. Okay. Whatever
name, the devil. Okay.
Just as when night falls on our
hemisphere or when a heavy fog is
blowing thick, a windmill seems to wheel
when seen far off. So then I seemed to
see that sort of structure. And next,
because the wind was strong, I shrank
behind my guide. There was no other
shelter. And now with fear, I set it
down in meter. I was where all the
shades were fully covered, but visible
as wisps of straw and glass. There's
some lie flat, another stand erect, one
on his head and one upon his souls, and
some bent face to feet just like a bow.
But after we had made our way ahead, my
master felt he now should have me see
that creature who was once a handsome
presence. He stepped aside and made me
stop and said, "Look, here is this." And
>> this this is just a name for for Luke or
Satan, okay?
>> And this the place where you will have
to arm yourself with fortitude. Oh
reader, do not ask of me how I grew
faint and frozen then. I cannot write
it. All words would fall fall far short
of what it was. I did not die and I was
not alive. Think for yourself, if you
have any wit, what I became, deprived of
life and death. The emperor of the
despondent kingdom so towered from the
ice up from midchest that I match better
with a giant's breath than giants match
the measure of his arms. Now you can
gauge the size of all of him if it is in
proportion to such part.
>> So basically this guy's a skyscraper.
Okay, he is huge. Keep on going.
>> If he was once as handsome and he now is
ugly and despite that raised his brows
against his maker. One can understand
how every sorrow has its source in him.
I marveled when I saw that on his head
he had three faces. one in front blood
red and then another two that just above
the midpoint of each shoulder joined the
first and at the crown all three were
reattached.
The right looked somewhat yellow,
somewhat white. The left in its
appearance was like those who come from
where the Nile descending flows beneath
each face of his two wings spread out as
broad as suited so immense a bird. I've
never seen a ship with sails so wide.
They had no feathers, but were fashioned
like a bats, and he was agitating them
so that three winds made their way out
of him, out from him,
and all causitus froze before those
winds. He wept out of six eyes and down
three chins. Tears gushed together with
a bloody froth. Within each mouth he
used it like a grinder. With nashing
teeth he tore to bits a sinner, so that
he brought much pain to three at once.
The forward sinner found that biting
nothing when matched against the clawing
for at times his back was stripped
completely of its hide. That soul up
there who is to suffer most. My master
said Judas a scariot his head inside. He
jerks his legs without. Of those two
others with their heads beneath the one
who hangs from that black snout is
Brutus. See how he rips and does not say
a word. That other who seems so robust
is Cashas.
But night has come again, and it is time
for us to leave. We have seen
everything.
Just as he asked, I clasped him around
the neck, and he watched for the chance
of time and place, and when the wings
were open wide enough,
he took fast hold upon the shaggy
flanks, and then descended down from
tough to tough between the tangled pair
and icy crusts. When he had reached when
we had reached the point at which the
thigh revolves just as the swelling of
the hip, my guide with heavy strain and
rugged work reversed his head to where
his legs had been and grappled on the
hair as one who climbs. I thought that
we were going back to hell.
Hold tight, my master said. He panted
like a man exhausted. It is by such
stairs that we must take our leaf of so
much evil. Then he slipped through a
crevice in a rock and placed me on the
edge of it to sit. That done he climbed
toward me with steady steps. I raised my
eyes believing I should see the the half
of Lucifer that I had left. Instead I
saw him with his legs turned up. And if
I then became perplexed, do let the
ignorant be judges, those who cannot
understand what point I had just
crossed. Get up, my master said, be on
your feet. The way is long, the path is
difficult. The sun's already back to
middle tears. It was no palace hall, the
place in which we found ourselves, but
with this rough hune floor and scanty
light, a dungeon built by nature.
Before I free myself from this abyss,
master, I said when I stood up straight.
Tell me enough to see I don't mistake.
Where's this ice and how's he so placed
head downward? Tell me to how has the
sun in so few hours gone from night to
morning? And he to me, you still believe
you're north of the center where I
grasped the hair of the damned worm who
pierces through the world. And you were
there as long as I descended. But when I
turned, that's when you passed the point
to which from every part all weights are
drawn. And now you stand beneath the
hemisphere opposing that which cloaks
the great dry lands and underneath whose
venth died the man whose birth and life
were sinless in this world. Your feet
are placed upon a little sphere that
forms the other face of the Judeeka.
Here it is morning when it's evening
there. And he whose hair has served us
as a ladder is still fixed even as he
was before. This was the sight on which
he fell from heaven for fear of him. The
land that once loomed here made of the
sea a veil and rose into our hemisphere.
And that land which appears upon this
side perhaps to flee from him left here
this hollow space and hurried upward.
There's a place below the limit of the
that cave its farthest point but from
beaselbub a place one cannot see. It is
discovered by ear. There is a sounding
stream that flows along the hollow of a
rock eroded by wind winding waters and
the slope is easy. My guide and I came
out came on that hidden road to make our
way back into the bright world and with
no care for any rest we climbed. He
first I following until I saw through a
round opening some of those things of
beauty heaven bears. It was from there
that we emerged to see once more the
stars. Okay, so the word we have for
kennel 34 is antilimatic. Okay, this is
not at all interesting or what we
expected. There's no
sense of relief. There's no sense of
drama. We build all the up all right to
this kanto and it's just like a huge
disappointment, right? We're expecting
this beautiful uh Lucifer who would
tempt us with poetry and uh I don't even
know what he is actually. Okay. Um so
this is really paradoxical. Again the
word is paradox. This makes no sense.
Dante is not a bad writer. He is a
briller.
So
How do you guys feel about this? Yes.
>> My initial sense is that he doesn't want
to risk priming us in any way bad. So
he's, as we've been saying, if his
poetry is priming us to put seeds in our
brain of interesting thoughts, he
doesn't even want to write the tempting
words that Satan might have said to him
down there in case it infects the reader
even slightly.
>> Is Satan capable capable of speech?
I can't remember reading anything in
this that says he's not. But
>> we know he's actually not capable of
speech. Why? Yeah. Yes.
Yeah. Yeah. Yes. Go ahead.
>> He's chewing on a sinners.
>> Yeah. So, his mouth is kind of busy, so
he can't actually speak. But what else?
Okay. All right. Did you have a comment?
Okay. We know he's actually not capable
of speech. Not just because he's his
mouth is busy, but also because why
he the lake in which he's frozen flips
no matter what aspect you look at him.
So he's frozen from the middle to either
extremity of his body and therefore
there's no way his being can
communicate.
>> Uh
yeah, that's interesting. Yes. Okay,
you're right. So, is he conscious?
Is he conscious?
Let me ask you this question. If there's
a mosquito on your neck, what do you do?
Yeah, you hit it obviously, right?
Is there a mosquito
on
uh Satan?
Is there a mosquito on Satan?
It's Virgil, man. What's he doing?
Nothing. Do you understand? He's not
even conscious.
What is he?
He's not conscious,
right? What is he really?
>> Uh NPC.
>> Uh I would say Yeah, I would say he's an
NPC. I'd say he's even worse than an
NPC.
What?
>> He's like a zombie.
>> No, he's even worse than a zombie.
Actually, you just look at it. Look at
the words that Donna used to describe
him, right?
>> Like robot.
>> He's even worse than a robot. What are
the words that Donna us to describe him?
He is a what?
H
he actually uses the certain words to
describe um the um the Lucifer.
What are the words he uses?
First of all, what what is what is
Lucifer doing? What is he like literally
doing?
>> It says he's the most It says he's a
ship.
What? I've never seen a ship with sail
so wide. So like
>> these words what what's the words?
>> A bird. He says a bat and a bird.
Where what what line?
>> Um well his wings are like
>> Yeah, his wings are like bats. But what
is he?
Read it carefully. What words are are
being used to describe
excuse me a grinder? Yes. What else?
There lot there lots of these. Grinder.
What else?
>> I think he said giant or like really big
at some point where finding the line.
Read read the poetry guys. He using
specific words to describe
uh
>> it's kind of animalistic.
the find me the words
>> he says as suited so they meant a bird
>> bird this is a simile right I'm saying
like what are the words that directly
>> number line six is blowing thick a
windmill seems to will and seem far off
>> so so windmill what what's the next line
>> and in seven he says so then I seem to
see that sort of structure
>> structure do you understand windmill
structure tower he is a building. Okay?
He is a machine.
That's all he is. He's not even a He's
not even conscious, right?
He's an air conditioner. That's
literally what he is. He's a giant air
conditioner blowing wind to cool the
lake.
Yeah, that's all he is. He's an ice
blower. Like, what is going on here?
Okay,
this makes no sense.
I think yeah, it's the paradoxical
source of cold. So if cold is molecules
vibrating less and less quickly,
somehow there has to be a source in this
magic universe and that's him,
>> right? So his punishment, his betrayal
is so great because he's betraying God
that his punishment is that he's lost
all consciousness right now. He's just a
machine. That is how low he sunk. He's
just a building. He's just uh Yes.
>> Like I was thinking if he is conscious
but he cannot do anything with his
situation, wouldn't that be like a worse
punishment? because now he is basically
gone and then there's just his like like
that it's it's just his physical being
that is in hell and not his conscious or
his soul. Like
wouldn't it be a worse punishment if he
knew what he was doing
about it?
>> Is that what you're saying? He's
comeoma. He's a vegetable
>> kind of. Okay. Um I don't Yeah. I mean
like like I just frozen, right?
Because consciousness requires
experience.
Yes.
>> Would venture to say that's his just
punishment,
>> right?
>> Lucifer's just punishment because
>> he was anything but. and now seems like
this powerless inert
frozen being that's just kind of not
even um at its will or has conscience
>> right yes okay
>> and it is also funny that if god is the
source of light and love and sun and you
know everything energy heat then Lucifer
it's a lack of so like going back to
paradis so kto one you Stanza one.
>> Exactly. The mirror the opposite.
>> That's right. Exactly right. And
remember like angels they all they they
can never turn away from God. Right. The
moment they turn away from God they
become this. Yes. [snorts]
>> Yeah. I wonder not just in an ethical
sense like um if God is all good but
just in a a capability sense like I'm
good at running um then having that lack
of good in the capable sense. Satan,
even like Ublino was good at being
clever and locking people into that
tower. And Satan is not good at anything
because he can't do anything.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, so, so I mean to answer
your question, is it possible he's
conscious but he can't move? And the
answer is if you're conscious, he would
be allowed to speak and talk about his
punishment, right? Does that make sense?
And the fact that he doesn't speak um
means he's not actually even conscious.
Uh yes.
But I think he does have some level of
comprehension because it does say that
he's crying.
>> Right. That that is correct. Yes, he
feels he is crying. Yes, that that's a
very interesting comment. Yes. And what
what do you make of this? Because he's
clearly not conscious.
>> Uh it's almost like that analogy of the
sort of vegetative state.
>> Okay. Yeah. So it's possible he's
conscious and he's crying. Yes. Uh yes.
>> Yeah. What I still don't really
understand is we say um Satan or Lucifer
was an angel but angels can never turn
away from God. So how did he turn away
from God?
>> That's a great question. Yes. Okay. That
that's also a paradox. Yes.
>> Uh I think Lucifer reminds me of a giant
data center. Uh it can host all kind of
programs, can process information, but
but uh ultimately it lacks it on soul.
>> Yeah. Exactly. So he's clearly a
machine. Okay. But but let's try to
figure out the question, okay? Because
[snorts]
all angels are staring at God. They're
turning towards God. Um and then Lucifer
turns away. Yes. I think this is quite a
prosaic interpretation, but because he's
the god of light, the sorry, the angel
of light, it is in his essence, darkness
is also essential to his being just by
being the angel of light. So, he's like
the most unlucky angel because of all of
the ones that would ever slip up and
turn to the darkness, it's going to be
him because as the angel of light,
that's the only way
um I can see.
>> Yeah. So, so what? Um, yes,
>> because I I've heard that the the God
loved the Lucifer mostly. So,
>> he's supposed to love God, right? He's
God's lieutenant.
>> Yeah. The love is is not limitation.
Maybe Ken, you know,
>> right? So, so it's it's possible he was
the lieutenant and he had free will. He
he screwed up.
>> Okay.
>> But then he wasn't an angel because
angels don't have a free will, right?
>> Right. No, but like remember when we
were up in paradiso, there are different
levels of angels. There are different
categories of of angels, right? So,
>> but we said all angels have no free
will. I thought
>> and conscious
>> or consciousness.
>> No, no consciousness and no free will.
>> Right. Right. Right. But but think think
of them as you know organs in a body,
right? They're they're all different.
They all serve a particular function.
And this particular organ uh Satan chose
to become a cancer. And so the body
threw him out. But what he didn't
recognize is that without the body, the
larger body, you you as an organ have
actually no no purpose. And so you just
decay and and and become um dead. Yeah.
But he could still choose. But he still
had a decision or he could make a
decision. But but like if you have if
you don't have a free will, then how can
you make a decision?
>> Yes. I think that he was God's number
two.
>> Yes. So that he didn't have free will,
but he was about as close as possible
that any celestial intelligence could
get that. I know it's a it's a it's
difficult for me as well, but I just
think that it's God proving that whoever
he gave like imagine he has to organize
his power in a certain way with amongst
angels to exact his will or whatever.
the one the his number two the one he
gives the most power to is the one most
likely to betray him and turn away and
have that capacity.
>> So was he was he always supposed to turn
away from him?
>> That's a kind of a theme in Paradise
Lost, but I'm not sure. It's a question
I can ask.
>> Okay. All right. So So let's let's first
talk about things we know. Okay. First
of all, we know that God's gift to
humanity was free will. And free will is
what distinguishes us from other beings.
Okay, that we know from uh paradiso. We
have free will and we can choose
whatever path we want. Uh that's uh
number one. Okay. Number two is the
functions of the angels in the heavens
is to basically
um be organs of a body, right? To
maintain the proper functioning of the
universe. Okay? So they don't actually
have free will. They're just um
basically servants. Okay. So
Lucifer was a headservant
and he doesn't have free will.
And so how does he turn away from God
then? He doesn't have free will.
How does he turn away from from from
God?
I just think it's in the nature of the
number two to eventually try to be
number one.
>> Yeah. It's it his nature has to be
disobedience. Okay. That's the only
thing that makes sense. Like it's his
nature to be disobedient. It is his will
to turn away from God. That is his
function. Turn away from God. Why that's
the case, I don't really know. Okay. So
when God constructed this hierarchy then
he must have willed this that he would
one day turn away.
>> Yeah.
>> So God so Okay.
>> Right. So the only thing that he cannot
will is it's us. He gave us free will.
Okay. But everything else he willed into
being.
>> Right.
Right. Yes. Sometimes I think this is a
little bit funny that it's almost like a
father whose son is really good at table
tennis, but the school he's sending his
son to doesn't play table tennis. So he
tries to get the school to play table
tennis before his son attends it. So God
let Satan destroy the world so that
Jesus would be able to have as big of an
impact as possible.
>> Yeah, that's I mean that's what
Christians believe, right? Okay. Um yeah
that that's the idea here like like
everything happens for a reason but if
that's the case okay this creates
another paradox which is there are three
betrayers right three people are being
punished and there these are the worst
offenders in human history and they are
Judas Escariat
they are Brutus and Casius Brutus and
Casius of course are the two who
assassinated Julius Caesar but we know
for a fact that there's a plan right the
plan is to uh create Christianity.
Buddhist and Cassus were crucial to this
plan because by killing Julius Caesar
that enable the rise of Augustus Caesar
and the Roman Empire. And then and then
Julius Scar is crucial this plan because
without him there'll be no there will be
no betrayal, right? And so Jesus would
not be crucified. So like if it's all
part of God's plan,
why would these three be punished?
Uh yeah,
>> because it's a vision being shown to
Dante to conscious minds that if you
showed that
evil people sometimes are part of God's
plan, I don't think that's a good image
to spread.
Okay. Yes.
>> I don't I don't know Dante would be a
determinist that he's been harping on
free will this.
>> That's right. That's right. So that
can't be the answer. Okay. Free will is
the fundamental law of the universe.
Okay. So why are these three being
punished?
>> Okay, so in theology I think they
explain it like this if I'm not mistaken
is that God has a plan for the world. He
sees the ultimate ending of all your
choices. He's kind of like AI, right?
Like he he can foresee like alpha go. He
can foresee your next step. He gives you
free will, right? As the competitor on
the other side of the go game. Um, so he
knows ultimately as AI can calculate by
mathematical formulas that you are going
to end up at this step. So like all the
betrayalers, God can see that they're
going to end up doing that. But God
doesn't control and make you like you
have to do that. But God just kind of
like silently watch behind the curtain
and be like, "Oh, you're going there.
Okay, then there will be Jesus or you're
going that then there will be the Holy
Roman Empire." So he doesn't interfere.
So he's not responsible for your fault.
So he's not willing, planning you,
predetermining you to make that fall.
But he kind of prepares like AI, he
prepares like options one to 12, you
know, depends on your, you know,
>> I understand that. But at the same time,
they are contributing to the vine plan,
right?
Go ahead.
>> I I'm speculating. I don't have a
conclusion yet.
All we're doing is okay because like
again if you you read all the commentary
the scholarship on Dante no one knows
what's going on like like what what's
going on here right?
>> Um um I want to follow up on that point
of
um just uh the the perception and how
psychedelics alters um the filters and
the ability for perception. It's almost
like God, the creator is putting up a
play for all us humans to watch. Um the
matrix, you know, whatever it is and um
it's for us to watch and perceive, but
even this is not reality.
>> Right. Okay.
>> And but it's meant to do something to
open you up.
>> Okay. Okay. Right.
I don't think Donnie is that
complicated. Let's let let's focus on
simple solutions. Okay.
Okay. So again like a razor we are
looking for elegance. So so that that
that's a great explanation. All these
are great explanations but I'm looking
for like a really elegant explanation
for what's going on. Okay. Let's move
towards elegance, clarity and simplicity
so that everyone understands. Uh yes.
>> Yes. Uh online uh chat. So how Lucifer
managed constant adversity for mortals
in any and every degree is God's will.
>> Okay. All right. Thank you for that. Uh
yes.
>> So we had said earlier Augustine claims
that God made hell and hell is good
because it's cosmic justice. You cannot
have free will without evil. I don't
know if Augustine comes to a
determination that God made evil or if
evil is a byproduct of free will, but it
seems like it they go hand in hand.
>> Okay. All right. So, um we're running
out of time. Okay. But but but but let
me explain what's going on. Okay. There
may be a divine plan. Doesn't matter.
Okay. Because we are the divine plan.
The imagination is the divine plan. And
so what what matters is not is this
advancing
um God's plan. That's not that's not
what matters. Okay. The results don't
matter. It's a process that matters.
What matters is what effect does it have
on us. Okay. Now Brutus and Casser are
important because how do they
assassinate Julius Caesar? Do you guys
do you guys know of Julius Caesar? Who
are these people? Brutus and Cas. Yes.
So I think Julius Caesar was about to
give a big speech and in the forum
before they beckoned him in and said,
"Let's have a meeting just prior to your
big address to the Senate." And then
they killed him.
>> Oh, no. But I'm saying like how do they
get access to Julius Caesar?
>> By being his friend, comrade, helper.
Yeah. Edu Bhutes. Okay. So you guys
don't know this, but there's speculation
that Brutus was his son. All right. So
remember this is this is um when was
Julius Susa assassinated? Like what what
year? 33. I can't I can't actually
remember when he was assassinated. Okay,
but it's like 10 years after the these
brutal civil wars when all these Romans
were trying to kill each other and and
then Julius Caesar was the only one left
standing and everyone around him so 44
BC okay but everyone around him were his
best friends his most loyal allies and
these were the people who betrayed him.
Do you understand? Okay. So, it goes
back to to the idea of betrayal of
guests. But what this is is the betrayal
of the host. Does it make sense? They
are guests in his house. He is basically
emperor now. And they Yes.
>> But is it not is it not even worse? Is
it because the Romans then later said
that Jew Caesar is a god? So, it's
betrayal of God maybe even.
>> Exactly. Exactly. That's right. after
Augustus Caesar comes in power, he
elevates
Julius Caesar to divinity. Okay, so this
is why they they're in hell because
Buddhism cast not only they did they
kill the host, right? But they killed
God himself.
>> That's but in the Christian from the
Christian view, it wouldn't be from
Dante, it wouldn't be a god like Jula
wouldn't be a god from Dante's view.
>> Yeah. But then the question then is who
is really massive of hell and who put
these guys there?
>> Virgil.
>> Probably Virgil. Okay. Okay, because we
know it's not Lucifer. Do you
understand? Okay, this is why Divine
Comedy, it is so brilliant because this
is a a Hollywood movie, but it's a shock
reveal. Do you understand? It's a shock
reveal. We thought Lucifer was the one
in charge, but it was Virgil all along.
Okay, because why else are Buddhist and
Cas
suffering like that? Okay, does that
make sense? This is the shock reveal.
All right.
But
has Dante been tempted by Virgil?
Right. We said that Lucifer's job is to
tempt
[clears throat]
um Jesus. Has Virgil tempted Dante?
Has he succeeded in attempting uh Dante?
>> Somewhat because earlier in the inferno
it seems fairly clear even if there are
some doubts that Dante does trust Virgil
as
>> guide. Yeah. How how does he how much
does he trust Virgil?
Okay. The scene is this right? What lets
him out of hell is Virgil climbs
Lucifer.
Where's Dante?
Virgil's the one climbing Lucifer,
right? Where where is Dante?
On the back of Virgil,
right? Do you understand this? Okay. So,
they're climbing out of hell and they go
into the sunlight.
What does this remind you of? This this
an allegory for what?
uh the like u medieval myth mythos of
saving and like abduction or saving like
the princess who's
>> much more much more simple than that. Uh
yes
>> like the ear the one that flew and that
got too close to the sun.
>> Oh, Icarus.
>> Icarus. Yeah.
>> Yes.
>> Oh, just stepping on the shoulders of
giants to reach ahead.
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah, that's an interesting
that that's what I'm thinking about.
Okay. Yes.
>> Birth.
>> Yes. It's birth, man. Right. Think about
how the mother takes you from the
darkness into the light for her own for
her exertion, right? It's marrying
birth.
It's hell. It's complete darkness.
And [clears throat]
Virgil is climbing Lucifer with Dante on
his back. And they go into the light.
It's exertion,
right?
So, has Virgil succeeded?
Yeah. He's made Dante into his son.
Once we leave Inferno, the temptation is
complete. It's a journey into
temptation,
right? It's a journey into sin, into
darkness. And now Dante is completely
beholden to Virgil as his son. Does that
make sense? Yes.
>> Yeah. Because later we see as well that
Dante misses Virgil.
>> Yes. That's right. Okay. Do you see how
beautiful this is? It's anticlimatic,
but it's perfect ending and it's it is
so symbolic,
right? Does that make sense to you guys?
All right. Any questions or comments
about this? Yes.
um metaphor kinds of makes me think
about oh it's so evangelical to say but
like so [laughter] that like our third
100 years on earth it's kind of like
this uh journey of in the mother's womb
and growing and learning about the
ultimate reality like Pluto said that he
has seen outside of the cave and so that
after this 100 years we are officially
entering eternal life to live life to
the fullest in heaven or whatever
places. So, it's kind of the same as
this ending. I feel like
>> exactly another comment I I'll make is
like that this the birth is an allegory
for Donnie reading the Iniad, right, in
Latin because at this time everyone
memorized the Iniad in Latin and it's
it's it's a really good way to learn
Latin by the way. So, it's so it's it's
a allegory for that like you reading a
lot you reading the ad is like Virgil
giving birth to you. Okay. So this is
this is again the beauty of blank
comedy. This now is a cliffhanger,
right? Because Lucifer has succeeded in
tempting Jesus that the temptation is
complete. And so the so now what's going
to happen is we know we we've read
paradise. Okay, we know that paradise
paradiso it is vision and revelation.
It mirrors
um the book of revelation. Okay, we know
that. We also know like inferno
is really prophecy. It is a criticism of
Italy. Okay. So, what purgatory has to
be is a
pilgrimage or a journey. Okay? It's
going to be literally a journey away
from Virgil and into Beatatrice,
away from hell and into heaven. Okay.
And this is this is like the grand
scheme of the line comedy. All right. So
when we come back, we're we're going to
look at how Virgil is really Lucifer.
All right. So enjoy your break. We'll
come back an hour. Um good afternoon. Um
so a couple of issues from this morning.
Okay. The first issue is why is Lucifer
crying? We said he was unconscious.
Uh we said he was just a building. Why
is he crying? Um this has to do with the
idea that all beings
aspire to be with God. Okay. The closer
you are to God, the happier you are. The
further away from God, the the uh
unhappier you are. And Lucifer because
of his betrayal, he is now permanently
away from God. And that's why he cries.
Uh he'll cry for all eternity. Also
remember in Limbo, even though Limbo is
a really nice retirement community, it's
just like Earth, a very nice um Italy,
um they're all sighing because they can
never be with God. Okay? So that's why
Lucifer is crying. That it doesn't
necessarily mean he's conscious um but
it just means that uh he's sad. Uh he
has the eternal unhappiness because he
is forever away from God. Second
question that we discussed this morning
that needs to be clarified is why did
Satan rebel? Okay. And I said something
really incorrect this morning which is
like angels do do not have free will. In
fact, they do have free will but they
have perfect free will which means they
have perfect obedience to God. Like once
you reach perfection, free will is
perfect obedience. Okay? And that's what
Oxen says in the uh city of God. So
imagine a situation where in the
beginning uh there were the angels and
um this is before God created us and the
angels they have free will and some
chose to rebel like Lucifer and some
chose of God and it's created the war in
heaven right uh and uh this something
that Milan writes about in paradise loss
but there's this war in heaven and those
who side with Lucifer they're cast into
hell and those who sit with God um
stayed in heaven and because they chose
God
uh they forever will look towards him
and can never look away from him because
they already made that choice and as
such uh heaven is able to reach
perfection. Okay. And this state of
affairs also foretells our fate where
remember there's a day of judgment and
the day of judgment is do you choose God
or do you choose Satan? Those who chase
choose Satan will be forever punished in
hell and those who cho choose um um God
will create heaven on heaven on earth.
Okay? It will literally be heaven coming
on earth. So that's the idea of um why
Satan rebelled. He w he had free will
and he chose to rebel uh because of his
pride. He wanted to be like God just as
like how Adam and Eve ate the food in
order to be like God.
And um this caused a war in heaven and
after this war um uh heaven became
perfect because everyone became
completely loyal to God. Does that make
sense? Okay. [clears throat]
So um
what we ended with this morning is the
idea that the real Satan, the real
master of hell is Virgil. Okay? And
that's why the Kanto is constructed the
way it is. So to further appreciate this
idea, what we're going to do is we're
going to go and reexamine Kanto 30.
Okay, KTO 30 there um we don't have to
go back yet, but Kandle 30, remember
there's this argument, this fight and it
broke up between Son and Master Adam.
Master Adam is a counterfeit and they're
trying to argue who's worse. Okay. Uh,
master Adam is a counterfeitter who
basically diluted gold to make Florence.
Florence is the uh currency of of
Florence. And at this point in history,
it is the most valuable currency mo the
most um credible currency in the world
because it's pure gold. And so when
[clears throat] Master Adam he um
dilutes the Florins, the the Floren burn
him at the stake. Okay, that's how they
that's how seriously they they took it.
Um, Son is the Greek soldier who tricked
the Trojans into letting in the Trojan
horse. Okay. And we're going to read um
the speech by Son to the Trojans that
convinced them to let in the Trojan
horse. And they're trying to argue who's
worse. uh the um the perjurer who is sin
on the false witness or the
counterfeitter um master Adam and we
have to think about why this fight is
happening. Remember, whenever Donnie
creates a paradox, the goal is to make
us think think much deeper about the
underlying uh message, the underlying
text. Okay. So, first thing we're going
to do is we're going to go and read the
Iniad and this is book two where Inias
is recounting the fall of Troy. And um
so if you know the history, what happens
is the Greeks try for 10 years to breach
the walls of Troy. They can't do it. So
like, okay, we're kind of stuck. And so
Ulisses proposes the Trojan horse. And
so they pretend to run away. The pre
pretend to run away. And they leave
behind the Trojan horse. And of course,
inside the Trojan horse are Ulyses,
Achily, Achilles, all the great Greek
champions. Um, it's a trap, right? And
the Trojans have the debate about what
to do with the horse. And everyone's
like, "Well, obviously this is a trap.
Let's just like burn it, man." And then
what what turns the tide is Son, the
Greek soldier, comes in and he tricks
the uh Trojans. Okay. So, we're just
we'll read a um you know, about a couple
hundred lines, but but I just want to
get get you a feel for what's going on.
Okay. All right. Uh can you read,
please?
Suddenly, in the thick of it all, a
young soldier, handshackled behind his
back, with much shouting, Trojan
shepherds were hailing him toward the
king. They'd come on the man by chance,
a total stranger. He'd given himself up
with one goal in mind, to open Troy to
the Greeks, and lay her waste. He
trusted to courage, nerve for either
end, to weave his lies or face his
certain death. Young Trojans's recruits,
keen to have a look, came scurrying up
from all sides, crowding round, outdoing
each other to make a mockery of the
captive. Now here the treachery of the
Greeks, and learn from a single crime
the nature of the beast, haggarded,
helpless, there in our midst he stood,
all eyes riveted on him now, and turning
a weary glance at the lines of Trojan
troops, he groaned and spoke. Where can
I find some refuge? Where on land, on
sea? What's left for me? A man of so
much misery. Nothing among the Greeks,
no place at all. And worse, I see my
Trojan enemies crying for my blood. His
groans convince me, cutting all our show
of violence short. We press him. Tell us
where you were born, your family. What
news do you bring? Tell us what you
trust to such a willing captive.
>> Okay, so this morning we talked about
Satan, right? How if Donnie were to meet
Satan then Satan would with poetry with
lyrical poetry tempt him and the first
thing that Satan would do is elicit his
sympathy right and that's exactly what
son is doing here going
>> all of it my king I'll tell you come
what may the whole true story Greek I am
I don't deny it now that first fortune
may have made me a man of misery but
wicked as she is She can't make sen a
lying fraud as well. Now perhaps you've
caught some rumor of calamities,
Bellis's son, and his shining fame that
rings in song. The Greeks charged him
with treason, a trumped up charge, an
innocent man, and just because he
opposed the war, they put him to death.
But once he's robbed of the light, they
mourn him sorely. Now I was his blood
kin. a youngster when my father, a poor
man, sent me off to the war at choice at
Palamedes as Palmeus's comrade. Long as
he kept his royal status, holding forth
in the councils of the kings, I had some
standing too, some pride of place. But
once he left the land of the living,
thanks to the jealous fork tongue of our
Ulyses, you're no stranger to his story.
I was shattered. I dragged out of my
life out my I dragged out my life in the
shadows, grieving, seething alone in
silence, outraged by my innocent
friend's demise until I burst out like a
madman. Swore if I ever returned and
triumphed to our native Argos, ever got
the chance, I'd take revenge, and my
oath provoked a storm of hatred. That
was my first step on the slippery road
to ruin. From then on, Ulisses kept
tormenting me, pressing charge on
charge. From then on, he brooded about
this two-edged rumors among the rank and
file. Driven by guilt, he looked for
ways to kill me. He never rested until
making calkets his henchmen. But why
now? Why go over that ungiving ground
again?
>> Let me stop. Okay. All right. All right.
So this is a very long speech but the
idea is with his poetry he's able to
elicit sympathy and that convinces the
Trojans to let in the Trojan horse even
though the common sense uh tells them we
shouldn't actually take gifts from
strangers. Okay, like we we shouldn't
actually let this thing in. We don't
know what it is. And that's really the
power of poetry. Okay, so that's Son and
that's why he's condemned to hell
because he hijacked people's imagination
in order to feed them a false narrative
that destroyed their city. Okay, now
we're going to Kanto 30 and I want to
reread the argument between Master Adam,
the counterfeitter, and Sion. Okay, so
this is line 91.
Count 30, Inferno uh line 91.
And this is after Master Adam told Dante
story of how he engaged in
counterfeiting. And so the Florentines
burn him at the stake.
>> And I to him, who are those two poor
poor sinners who give off smoke like wet
hands in the winter and lie so close to
you upon the right? I found them here,
he answered, when I rained down to this
rocky slope. They've not stirred since
and will not move I think eternally. One
is the lying woman who blames Joseph.
The other lying
Greek from Troy because of raging fever
they so. And one of them who seemed to
take offense perhaps at being named so
squalibly struck with his fist at Adam's
rigid belly.
>> Okay. So I thought just asking Adam who
are these other two people being
punished here and Adam's like well. And
so he names them and one of them Simon
who for all eternity has not stirred. He
just just lies there in a raging favor.
That fever that's his punishment. He
hears his name and gets really angry and
he takes takes offense and and punches
Adam. Okay, keep on going.
It sounded as if it had been a drum, and
Master Adam struck him in the face using
his arm, which did not seem less hard,
saying to him, "Although I cannot move
my limbs because they're too heavy, I
still have an arm that's free to serve
that need." And he replied, "But when
you went to burning, your arm was not as
quick as it was now. Though when you
coined, it was as quick as more."
>> So now they're just um insulting each
other. Okay. Uh keep on going.
to which the drop seed one hear you
speak true but you were not so true a
witness there when you were asked to
tell the truth at Troy if I spoke false
you falsified the coin said son I'm here
for just one crime but you've committed
more than any demon
>> so son's like well I spoke false but you
falsified the coin right and in most
country in every country you would get
punished a lot more for counterfeiting
than you would for lying right In fact,
um I I I think the worst punishment is
counterfeiting, right? Uh sorry, the
worst crime is counterfeiting, right? Um
what does a secret service do in the
United States? It it looks for
counterfeits. Okay? It's a very serious
thing. And when Isaac Newton was head of
the mint in in the in the in England, if
he c if he caught you counterfeiting, he
would like basically uh torture you to
death. Okay? It's a very serious thing.
And so s's like just pointing this out.
Point this out. Like you fing on the
coins is a lot worse than what I did.
All I did was just lie. Right. Uh keep
on going.
>> Not forget the horse you perjurer
replied the one who had the bloated
valley. May you be plagued because the
whole world knows it.
>> And what Adam says is that for your lie
you let the trojans let in the children
and that destroy the children
civilization. Okay. Uh so the conse
consequences were much worse.
and you be plagued by thirst that cracks
your tongue and putrid water that has
made your belly such a hedge before your
eyes. And then the corner, so as usual,
your mouth because of racking fever
gapes. For if I thirst and if my humor
bloats me, you have both dryness and a
head that aches. Few words would be
sufficient imitation to have you lick
the mirror of narcissists.
I was intent on listening to them when
this was what my master said. If you
insist on looking more, I'll quarrel
with you." And when I heard him speak so
angrily, I turned around to him with
shame so great that it still stirs
within my memory.
>> Okay. So, what is um strange about this?
What's going on? What What stands out
about this story, about this passage?
What does Virgil do here that he's never
done before and he'll never do again?
Actually,
>> he's stopping the conversation. is
stopping Dante from digging deeper.
>> Okay. But he's done that before, right?
He's switched topics. He's uh but but
he's but here he's he's doing something
that he's never done before and he'll
never do again.
>> He threatened Dante.
>> He's angry with Dante, right? He's never
done that before. Okay. So, what what's
he angry about? Why is he angry?
All right. So, the paradox is this.
Okay.
Virgil is angry at Dante because Dante
is watching a fight between Master Adam
and Son,
right? And and Master Adam and Son are
arguing who's worse. U Master Adam says
you counterfeited the coin
so you're worse. And then what should
mass Adam's response be? You count the
counterfeit the coin. That's pretty bad.
But something actually worse than
counterfeiting the coin, which is what?
>> Yes.
>> Counterfeiting a gift in the sense that
it's a poisoned gift.
>> Um, that's interesting. What's the worst
thing you can do in university?
Plagiarism. Right. Plagiarism. Plagium
is a lot worse than counterfeiting the
coin, right? If you're at university and
you started to counterfeit money, yeah,
they might throw you in prison, but if
you plagiarized, you would be thrown out
of university forever.
But so
what is son plagiarizing? Do you do you
guys know?
Is it something that somebody says in
the Bible that
>> you read the Iniad, right? What is that
plagiarizing?
>> I can't remember. I'm sorry.
>> You guys don't learn this in school.
>> It was just for Latin translation, too.
>> Oh, okay. So, you read parts of it.
>> The major parts. Yeah. But
>> what what does plagiarizing mean?
>> Oh, plagiarism means to steal ideas from
other people and pretend it's your own.
Well, he stole poetry maybe
>> from who?
>> Virgil and not at Homer.
>> Yeah. So Virgil stole from Homer, right?
The Iniad stole from the Iliad and the
Odyssey and it corrupted the Iliad in
the Odyssey. Much the way that a
counterfeitter corrupts coin, right?
>> You understand? A counterfeitter takes
real gold, dilutes it, add some lead,
and pretend it's real gold. A what
Virgil did was he stole from the Aladdin
Odyssey, polluted it and pretend it's
real poetry.
Do you understand? Okay. So, this is
drawing attention to the fact that
basically Virgil plagiarized
uh Homer and this and this is why Virgil
is angry because what what does a
plagiarizer hate the most
to me?
being found out, right? Being accused of
plagiarism,
right? Um, and so Virgil's very, very
angry. What's the paradox here?
[clears throat]
Excuse me.
>> Is it that he's the guide to hell?
>> Yeah. Like, why is Son burning here and
Virgil's okay? Right. Because it's
Virgil who created the character Son
and allow Son to lie. It's not Son
that's a problem. It's the Inads that's
that's a problem.
Okay. Does that make sense? Yes.
>> Like before he died he was like please
burn all this stuff. That means that his
consciousness knows that what he did was
wrong. So he sort of repented before he
died.
>> Yeah. But if he repented then where
where should he be?
>> Uh heaven. No, actually
>> Nimbo, but which he is, but
>> No, no, he should be in purgatory.
>> Oh, purgatory. Right.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, that's not the answer.
Okay. It's possible, right? But again,
this is raising a paradox, which is like
why is Son here when the real culprit,
Virgil, the plagiarist, he's walking
free around hell? He's able to control
hell. He's able to uh decide uh that
cases and Buddhists will be tortured by
Lucifer. Yes.
>> Well, I think because Simon actually
believes that he did something wrong and
Virgil believes that he did nothing
wrong when he stole. So I think Virgil
already forgived himself for what he
did, but Simon can forgive himself for
what he did to the to the Trojans.
Okay. Um, that's interesting. Okay. Does
Son think he did anything wrong?
He knows he lied, but he did he do
anything wrong.
>> Is it that Virgil admits that he did
plagiarism by being angry at being
accused of plagiarism?
>> Well, no. He's angry because he doesn't
want to admit it, right?
Okay. So again, this could all this
creates all these paradoxes here. And so
I want I want you guys to keep this at
the back of your mind. Why is it
that Virgil is not punished at all for
his crimes?
And why is hell structured the way it
is? Uh yes.
But if Virgil is basically like Lucifer,
then his main aim is to deceive Dante.
So therefore, he can't in front of Dante
be seem to be punished for his sins.
>> Uh but I I don't understand this. His
main aim is to deceive Dante, to tempt
Dante. I understand that. But why would
he be allowed to do that?
>> Uh yes,
>> I think that
He's made the master of hell. And one of
the key things of the anid was about
duty and the killing of turnis. And I
was thinking about this why it's such a
beautiful thing that Virgil is the guide
and master of hell that many many people
who sin do so because they're they feel
forced by themselves. And so Virgil's
not being punished, but his punishment
is that he has to guide everybody around
because it's the very force that the
Anerid put into people's hearts that
made them sin in years to come.
>> Um, okay. That's interesting. But, but,
uh, the fact is that Virgil is not not
the guide of hell. He's got the guy to
Dante. He's he was appointed by
Beatatric to be the guide, but he's
usually in limbo. Okay. But he can run
around hell. He's very he knows hell
very well, right? If he's able to climb
uh Lucifer, then he knows hell like the
back of his hand. So, but but but again,
these are all paradoxes and as we go
into uh purgatory, the answers will be
revealed to us. Okay. All right. So,
this is purgatory one.
Purgatory Cantal one to course across
more kindly waters. Now my talent's
little vessel lives her sails leaving
behind herself a sea so cruel and what I
sing will be that second kingdom in
which the human soul is cleansed of sin
becoming worthy of ascent to heaven. But
here since I am yours, oh holy muses,
may this poem rise again from hell's
dead realm. And may Calopi rise somewhat
here accompanying my singing with that
music whose power struck the poor
pierodis so forcefully that they
despared a pardon. The gentle hue of
oriental sapphire in which the sky
serenity was steeped its aspect is
aspect pure as far as the horizon.
>> Okay. So let me test your memory. Okay.
So again there's parallels parallelism
uh symmetry in divine comedy.
Um here he's saying I want I now want to
write about purgatory. I now sing about
purgatory. So muses come and give me
inspiration. Okay.
In paradise when he was writing about
the heavens who did he call to inspire
him?
Apollo and the muses. Okay. Do you
understand? So he's saying here
purgatory uh the muses inspire me. But
in heaven, I need everyone. Apollo, the
muses, everyone to fully inspire me.
Okay, keep on going.
Line 16. Brought back my joy in seeing
just as noon, as I had left behind the
air of death that had afflicted both my
sight and breast. The lovely planet that
is patronis of love made all the eastern
heavens glad, veiling the Pisces in the
train she led. Then I turned to the
right, setting my mind upon the the
other pole, and saw four stars not seen
before, except by the first people.
Heaven appeared to revel in their
flames. Oh, northern hemisphere, because
you were denied that sight. You're a
widowerower. After my eyes took leave of
those four four stars, turning a little
toward the other pole from which the
Wayne had disappeared by now, I saw a
solitary patriarch near me. His aspect
worthy of such reverence that even son
to father owes no more. His beard was
long and mixed with white as were the
hairs upon his head, and his hair spread
down to his chest in a divided dress.
The rays of the four holy stars so
framed his face with light that in my
sight he seemed like one who's
confronted by the sun.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, so the solitary
patriarch, he is the master of purgatory
and his name is Kato.
Can someone tell me why having Kato as a
master of purgatory is such a paradox?
Yes.
>> Because he was born before the time of
Jesus. So he should be in limbo.
>> Exactly. Okay. Number one is he is not a
Christian.
He is not a Christian. Virgil told us
explicitly that unless you are baptized,
you cannot leave limbo. Uh yes,
>> I think if my memory serves historically
that Kato was seen to be somebody who
was so talented that whenever he did
anything it was like he had done it from
birth like like he knew how to do it
from birth. So for him to be the master
of purgatory that you live and then this
is your journey to heaven, it's ironic
because he seemed to have grasped
everything very quickly in his life.
>> Okay. Sure. Okay. But but but that's not
necessarily a paradox. Like the fact
that he is not a Christian,
that's a paradox. But there are some
other paradoxes as well. Why should kill
not be in purgatory? In fact, he should
be infernal. Why?
Was
he amongst the people who killed Caesar?
>> No, but he rebelled against Caesar,
>> right?
>> He rebelled against Caesar. He was on
the side of um Pompei.
Um so if I'm I'm trying to figure this
out. If Julius Caesar is in limbo and if
the people who killed Julius Caesar uh
Buddhist and Casius are the worst people
in the world and Kato
fought against Caesar.
Why is Caesar master of purgatory? Okay,
that's that's another paradox. And
there's one more paradox and it's
actually the most this is actually the
biggest paradox. How did he die?
Suicide, right? Suicide
in Catholic theology at this time.
Suicide go straight to hell. No
questions, no doubts. Straight to hell,
guys. Okay, so we have three axes
against Ko. He's not a Christian. He
rebelled against Caesar and he killed
himself. Okay, so he should be in a
circle of violence with the other people
who committed suicide. He used to be a
tree and now he's massive purgatory. So,
something is really weird going on.
Okay. Uh, yes.
>> I'm not sure how he why he committed
suicide, but I would guess it's because
of his honor for um whatever um the side
that he served for for Pompei. I would
guess maybe
>> he committed suicide because his side
was losing and Caesar was offering
clemency to everyone, right? And so what
was going to happen is Caesar would have
come to Ko and says, "Ko, I forgive you
and will you please be a senator?" And
Ko's like, "I don't want this crap. I'm
going to kill myself because that's the
honorable thing to do." Right? He he did
not want to give Julius Caesar the
opportunity to show clemency.
So that's pretty bad, right? [laughter]
I mean, to kill yourself for this like
like it's kind of petty really, right?
All right. Um, so that's Ko
and Ko and Virgil knew each other,
right? They're they are contemporaries.
So Virgil and Dante are now in
purgatory. Ko comes up and he sees
Virgil. How should he react?
I mean, how would you react if you saw
someone from like a a a previous life?
Yeah, you'd be pretty happy, right?
You'd be pretty happy. Like a childhood
best friend who you haven't seen for
like 40 years. You're like, "Oh my god,
I run into you in the streets of Rome.
Let's chat. Let's get a coffee. Let's
reminisce." Right. Yes.
Is is this a suspicion that Virgil put
Kato there in some way or or that he was
responsible for Kato being placed there
>> in purgatory? Okay. Because Virgil,
where's Virgil
>> at this moment or in general? In
general. In limbo? In limbo?
>> In limbo, right? And why in limbo?
because he was brought up there as by
there there's only one reason why he he
he's in limbo according to to to Virgil.
He's not a Christian, right? He was not
baptized as a Christian. That's the only
reason, right? So, it doesn't make any
sense why he would uh tell us this and
then put Ko in purgatory. Okay. All
right. So, yeah, we would imagine that
Virgil and Ko are good friends and it
would be a happy reunion. Okay. Uh let's
keep on reading
>> line 40.
Who are you? Who against the hidden
river were able to escape the eternal
prison? He said, moving those venerable
plumes. Who was your guide? What served
you both as lantern when from the deep
night that will always keep the hellish
valley dark you were set free? The loss
of the abyss. Have they been broken? Or
has a new changed decree in heaven let
you though damned approach my rocky
slopes?
>> There's a really ironic sentence here.
What is it?
What's a really ironic sentence in the
speech?
It's really ironic.
Nope.
Where's your kid be?
He should be in limbo at least, right?
So So what does he say that? That's kind
of ironic. It's like uh what?
That he knows what hell is like?
>> No, no. I'm saying like what did he say
in the speech? That's ironic.
>> Were you able to escape?
>> Yeah. Like how did you get here? It's
like, well, okay, Ko, but how did you
get here? Right. That's kind of ironic,
right? How are you able to escape the
eternal prison? The ideal prison is like
no one can escape it, but he did. All
right. So, it's ironic.
All right. Uh, keep on going.
Line 49. My guide took hold of me
decisively by way of words and hands and
other signs. He made my knees and brow
show reverence. Then he replied, "I do
not come through my own self. There was
a lady sent from heaven. Her, please let
me to help and guide this man. But since
your will would have a far more full and
accurate account of our condition, my
will cannot withhold what you request."
This man had yet to see his final
evening, but through his folly, little
time was left before he did. He was so
close to it. As I have told you, I was
sent to him for his deliverance. The
only rule road I could have taken was
the road I took. I showed him all the
people of predition. Now I intend to
show to him those spirits who in your
care are bent on experation. To tell you
how I led him would take take long. It
is a power descending from above that
help me guide him here to see and hear
you. Now may it please you to prove his
coming. He goes in search of liberty. So
precious as he who gives his life for it
must know. You know it. who in Utica
found death for freedom was not bitter
when you left the garb that will be
bright on the great day.
>> Okay. So he's ref referencing Virgil is
referencing how Ko killed himself in
Udica rather than submit to Caesar.
Okay. All right. Come on.
>> Line 76. Eternal edicts are not broken
for us. This man's alive and I'm not
bound by Minos. But I am from the circle
where the chased eyes of your marsha
are. And she still prays to you, oh holy
breast, to keep her as your own for her
love then inclined to us. Allow our
journey through your southern realms. I
shall thank her for kindness you bestow.
If you would let your name be named
below.
>> Okay. So, um, Virgil is telling, uh,
Kato,
uh, why they they're they're here, and
Virgil explains that Dante is not dead,
so he can move around. And he he who was
not never sentenced to the inner circles
of hell, so he's free to move around.
And also, Ko, hey, uh, your wife Marcia,
she's with me, and if you help us, then
I'll go back and help Marcia. Okay.
Does it sound like friends to you?
All right, we'll keep on reading. Okay.
>> 9
85.
While I was there within the other
world, Masia so pleased my eyes, he then
replied, "Each kindness you required, I
satisfied."
>> Okay. So, he's saying before, he was in
limbo.
Okay. Right. Before I was in limbo of
Marcia. Keep on going.
>> Now that she dwells beyond the evil
river, she has no power to move me any
longer. Such was the law decreed when I
was freed. But if a lady come from
heaven speeds and helps you, as you say,
there's no need of flattery. It is
enough indeed to ask me for her sake. Go
then, but first wind a smooth brush
around his waist and bathe his face to
wash away all of hell's stains. For it
would not be seemly to approach with
eyes still dimmed by any mists. The
first custodian angel one from paradise.
This solitary island all around its very
base there where the breakers pound
bears rushes on a soft and muddy ground.
There's no other plant that lives below.
No plant with leaves or plant that as it
grows hardens and breaks beneath the
waves harsh blows that done do not
return by this same pass. The sun which
rises now will show you how this
hillside can be climbed more easily.
>> So um
Virgil says
how does K respond to Virgil's speech?
Anyone
>> rather sarcastic
or or or
>> does he like does he like Virgil? He
hates Virgil.
>> He's like, "Don't mention Marcia to me,
you asshole."
Okay,
>> I want to help you because Beatrice uh
told me to, but that's why. Not because
uh you can help Marcia.
Okay. So, they're they're like enemies.
They don't really like each other.
And this makes you question who Virgil
really is, right? What is Ko not like U
Virgil? Yes.
>> Um in in line 95 96 he tells him um that
his face and body should be washed of
hell basically. So he he knows that
Virgil is hell itself or like he he has
so much so many like
>> yeah this is a really really interesting
reading right so literally just means
Dante has been through hell and his face
is dirty right because hell is like lots
of dirt and fire so go wash your face
because this is purgatory and but you
can also say that it's metaphorical in
that Um, Virgil has corrupted Dante in
this journey by feeding him a lot of
lies about
um about hell. So, what's important is
for Dante to begin to cleanse himself of
Virgil's lies. Okay. Right. To remove
Virgil's influence from himself. Yeah.
That that that's a very interesting
reading. Yes. Okay. All right. Uh let's
let's keep on reading.
9 109 With that he vanished and without
a word I rose and drew in closer to my
guide and it was on him that I set my
eyes and he began sun followed my steps.
Let us go back. This is the point at
which the plain slopes down to reach its
lowest bound. Daybreak was vanquishing
the dark last hour which fled before it
in the distance. I could recognize the
trembling of the sea. We made our way
across the lonely plain like one
returning to a lost pathway who till he
finds it seems to move in vain. When we
had reached the point where Dio contends
the sun and undersea winds and the shade
winds out because it won't evaporate. My
master gently placed both of his hands
outspread upon the grass. Therefore,
aware of what his gesture and intention
were, I reached and offered him my tear
strained cheeks, and on my cheeks he
totally revealed the color that inferno
had concealed. Then we arrived at the
deserted shore, which never yet had seen
its waters coursed by any man who
journeyed back again. There, just as
pleased another, he g me. Oh wonder
where he plucked the humble plant that
he had chosen. There that plant sprang
up again identical immediately.
>> Okay, so we are um in the beaches of
purgatory. Okay, so purgatory is a
mountain and in order to cleanse
yourself, you climb up this mountain and
in each terrace of the mountain, you
have to do an activity to cleanse
yourself of the seven um uh deadly sins.
Um but we are not on the mountain yet.
We are outside the mountain on the
beaches. This is something a place
called anti-purgatory which is people
who uh repentant late in life and so
they must wait and fully uh serve their
penance before they're allowed to enter
purgatory. Once they enter purgatory and
they cleanse themselves then they are
able to ascend to heaven. Okay. Uh yes.
>> So is there a sense of time in
purgatory?
>> Uh that's a really good question. Um, so
what Dante is going to do a lot is talk
about the sun rise. Okay. And um, one
thing that's really important us to keep
in mind is that the rules governing
purgatory are different from the rules
governing hell. Hell is like eternal
torment. There's no time. It's all just
fire and darkness. But in purgatory,
there's night and day. And you can only
climb during the day. At night, you have
to rest. And it's gonna be very
important for us because during the
night you dream, right? Um, so the
dreams are going to be very uh important
as well. Okay. So there's time, but I
don't I don't but like I don't know how
to tell time because a lot of of this is
astronomy, right? Reading the stars,
figure out where the sun is. And I I I
actually don't know how that works.
Okay. Because you say that the the the
mind creates time and space to
uh to
um see reality or like to percept
reality.
>> Why did we create time in purgatory to
accept purgatory or like it's time out
of ourselves in that sense?
>> Okay, this is a really interesting
question because one very important idea
in purgatory is that you have to serve
your time, right? It could be a million
years and it could be a thousand years.
And so I think the idea of time in
purgatory is it's not physical time,
right? It's not like, you know, you
actually uh keep a clock and you wait
10,000 years. [snorts] It's really about
emotional time. So basically, it's like
you're meditating and you're med you're
meditating and trying to cleanse your
soul. And um it doesn't we don't
actually know physically how much time
it takes. Okay. But there there is a
time element to it. Does that make
sense? Okay. So so um um I really don't
understand time well in purgatory. Okay.
All right. Uh let's let's keep reading.
Kanto 2.
By now the sun was crossing the horizon
of the meridian whose highest point
covered Jerusalem and from the Ganges
night circling opposite the sun was
moving together with the scales that
when the length of dark defeat the day
desert knight's hands so that above the
shore that I had reached the fair
aurora's white and scarlet cheeks were
as Aurora aged becoming orange. We still
were by the sea like those who think
about the journey they will undertake,
who go in heart but in the body stay.
And just as Mars, when it is overcome by
the invading mists of dawn, glows red
above the wat's plane low in the west,
so there appeared to me, and may I see
it again, a light that crossed the sea,
so swift there's no flight of bird to
equal it. When for a moment I'd
withdrawn my eyes that I might ask the
question of my guide, I saw that light
again, larger, more bright.
>> Okay. Sorry. Okay. So to continue your
your question, um clearly there's time
here, right? And there was no time in
hell. So um we we discussed how we
create time and space with our uh
imagination. So um I think the idea here
is that in hell we're just trapped in
hell. There is no time in space because
um we're just trapped there. Whereas in
purgatory
um there's now motion meaning there is
now free will meaning there is now
agency. There's more um you you can now
act actively participate in life.
There's not does that make sense?
>> Yeah. But KTO was uh no Kato was in hell
before, right? So how did he escape
without
a free will? If you say there's no free
will in in hell. Yeah, that that that
again is a paradox. Okay. And here we
will just have to use our imagination.
Does anyone know how we can resolve this
paradox?
Yes.
And my memory is quite hazy, but I
thought that
maybe it was Jesus or some redeeming
force who is shunting people up. Shunted
the very best souls up from inferno and
that they didn't make it to heaven, but
then they were either in limbo or
therefore in purgatory.
>> Exactly. Yeah. So what we know is that
Jesus did take away with him the best
souls, but the people he took were like
off the Hebrew Bible, right? David,
Abraham, Moses. What is Ko doing with
them?
Okay, so this is hard. Okay, but one
possible solution is this.
Um
so
what we learn in paradise is that uh
there are certain people who are born
before the time of Jesus.
And even though they were not officially
Christian and that they were baptized,
they were Christian that their heart was
in the right place. Okay? And they knew
that Jesus was coming. And so they they
prepared for the coming of Jesus even
though they did not see Jesus in their
lifetime. Does that make sense? And Ko
must have been one of these individuals
who knew Jesus was coming and he
submitted himself before Jesus
even though and he didn't live long
enough for the coming of Jesus. And when
Jesus went down to hell, he could see
um that Ko even though he was not
officially Christian, he was in his
heart Christian.
Okay. Does that make sense guys? Yes.
with the Catholic doctrine as well. the
kate is very well um embracing not
really but I don't know what's the right
word but yeah of the people who
fundamentally in essence has this
doctrines or you know leave out the life
of faith however you define faith but
yeah
>> yeah and and and and later on we will
discover people who who are actually
like that okay they did not convert to
Christianity in their lifetime but in
their hearts they were Christian okay uh
before Jesus is came they were already
Christian and that's why they were able
to ascend to purgatory as well as to
paradise okay we'll learn more about
this later on right uh yes
>> yeah so but I have question because just
you said only your heart is not enough
for you to go to the heaven but you have
to baptize right or
>> yeah but but but that's what they're
saying here it's not the act that
matters it's the heart that matters it's
the will and the desire that matters
okay um okay yes
Jesus also said that greater is the he
who has faith before he has seen it. So
it's a lot of these people before he was
born sort of believed in him or believe
in some sort of this idea of redemption
a messiah then they have greater faith
than the disciples like Peter or John
who has seen and put their hands through
Jesus Peter's hands uh that you know
these forefathers whoever they are in
the earth yeah deserves.
>> Yes. Okay. So that that's a logic. Okay.
And and again, we'll never know. It's
it's a paradox created uh by divine
comedy. But this is one way to resolve
this paradox. All right. Okay.
>> Line 22. Then to each side of it I saw a
whiteness, though I did not know what
the whiteness was. Below another
whiteness slowly showed. My master did
not say a word before the whitenesses
first seen appeared as wings. But then
when he had recognized the helmsmen, he
cried, "Ben, bend your knees. Behold the
angel of God and join your hands. From
this point on, this is the kind of
minister you'll meet.
>> Okay? So, it's these angels that are
guardians of purgatory. Okay? Before in
hell, there were these demons. Now,
there are these angels. So, at each
major checkpoint, there are these
angels. Uh, keep on going.
>> Line 31. See how much scorn he has for
human means. He'd have he'd have no
other sail than his own wings, and use
no ore between such distant shores. See
how he holds his wings pointing to
heaven, piercing the air with his
eternal pine, which do not change as
mortal plumage does. Then he, that bird
divine, as he drew closer and closer to
us, seemed to gain in brightness, so
that my eyes could not endure his
nearness. And I was forced to lower
them, and he came onto shore with boats
so light, so quick that nowhere did the
water swallow it. The helmsman sent from
heaven at the stern seemed to have
blessedness inscribed upon him. More
than a hundred spirits sat within intu
Israel day agyptu with what is written
after that psalm of all of the spirits
sang as with one voice.
Then over them he made the holy cross a
sign. They flung themselves down on the
shore and he moved off as he had come
swiftly. The crowd that he had left
belonged the beach seemed not to know
the place. They looked about like those
whose eyes try out things new to them.
Upon all sides the sunshot forth the
day, and from midheaven its incisive
arrows already had chased Capricorn
away, when those who just arrived lifted
their heads toward us and said, "Do show
us, if you know, the way by which we can
ascend the slope." And Virgil answered,
"You may be convinced that we're quite
familiar with this shore, but we're
strangers here just as you are. We came
but now a little while before you,
though by another path so difficult and
dense that this ascent seems sport to
us."
The souls who, noticing my breathing,
sensed that I was still a living being,
then out of astonishment turned pale.
And just as people crowd around a
messenger who bears an olive branch to
hear his news, and no one hesitates to
join that crush. So here those happy
spirits, all of them stir hard at my
face, just as if they had forgotten to
proceed to their perfection.
I saw one of those spirits moving
forward in order to embrace me. His
affection so great that I was moved to
mime his welcome.
>> Hey, stop. Okay. All right. So again,
this is mirroring hell. Remember,
remember how um when Virgil took uh
Dante into hell, they have to cross the
river Aaron, right? And there's all
these souls lining up to cross the
river.
And the same thing is happening here
where there's souls lining up to cross
the river into antip purgatory, uh the
area before the mountain.
Can you explain to me or just list for
me the differences between these two
groups? The first group in hell, second
group improvatory. What are the
differences you notice? It's pretty
stark actually the these differences.
What are they doing here that souls
didn't do in hell?
>> Looking around for new.
>> This is very important. Okay, you
understand? They're curious.
Okay, remember and like it's very
explicit uh the line right um their eyes
try look line look at line 54 whose eyes
try things new to them they're curious
they want to learn
okay it's pretty stark that's one
they're curious what's the other thing
Yes.
>> Uh asking about the place
>> they ask, they talk, man. Think about
it. How in how in uh in hell the souls
just didn't talk,
right? They talk. They asked questions.
Yes.
>> I feel like in spirit they feel a lot
more optimistic.
>> Yeah. Yeah. They're active, right?
Whereas uh in infernal they were
passive. They were just indifferent.
Nothing could move them. Uh yes.
73. So here those happy spirits, all of
them stare hard at my face. So it's like
they're really happy. Like people in
hell just not very happy.
>> That's right. They're happy. They're
optimistic. Exactly. Yes. And also what
are they doing that that never happens
in hell?
They're embracing each other. They're
touching each other. Uh what else?
What what are they doing here? That
never happens in hell but happens a lot
in heaven
seeing right look look at line 46
right 46 to 48 those spirits sang with
one voice okay so this is a pretty
strict economy
right that the souls in hell were
passive indifferent they just accept
their fate whereas here the souls are
curious ious. They want to learn. So, so
what's this really saying about who's in
hell and who and who's in purgatory
who who goes to hell, who goes to
purgatory? I guess
hell is a place of inactivity or being
very passive and no curiosity, no
consciousness, no wanting to learn or
improve, no agency. And then purgatory
is like we sin a little bit, but we're
still happy. We still want to try to get
better. We are just people at fault, but
we we are still trying.
>> Exactly. Yes.
>> Just similar to that that they have an
optimistic mindset, a growth mindset.
>> It's attitude, right? It's they choose.
It's like um
do you guys know Cara Dwight? Right.
Carol Carol Dwight. Dwight. Yeah, you
probably know her. Um but you know she's
a Stanford psychologist and she says
that in life there are those who succeed
and those who fail and the main
difference is in attitude right those
who succeed have a growth mindset which
is say they're always looking to get
better okay they accept adversity they
accept failure as opportunities to
improve themselves whereas fixed people
fixed mindset don't believe they can
ever improve and they just accept things
as they are afraid a failure. Okay. And
that's the difference between uh hell
and purgatory.
Okay. So this is radical because Kano
shows us it's not necessarily what you
do that condemns you to hell or
purgatory. It's what your attitude is,
what you believe, what you choose to do
that's important. Okay? Your mindset
that's important. Okay? Does that make
sense? All right. Uh let's let's keep on
reading.
>> Line 79. Oh shades in all except
appearance empty. Three times I clasped
my hands behind him and often brought
them back against my chest. Dismay I
think was painted on my face at this
that shadow smiled as he withdrew and I
still seeking him again advanced. Gently
he said that I could now stand back.
Then I knew who he was and I beseeched
him to remain a while and talk with me.
He answered, "As I loved you when I was
within my mortal flesh, so freed I love
you, therefore I stay." But you, why do
you journey? My own Cassella to return
again to where I am, I journey thus. But
why, I said, were you deprived of so
much time? And he no injury is done to
me if he whose takes up whom and when he
pleases has kept me from this crossing
many times. For his own will derives
from a just will and yet for three
months now he has accepted more most
tranquily all those who would embark.
Therefore I who had turned then to the
shore at which the tyers water makes the
salt was gathered in by his benevolence.
Straight to that river mouth he set his
wings. that always is the place of
gathering for those who do not sink to
Aaron.
And I, if there's no new law that denies
you memory or practice of the songs of
love that used to quiet all my longings,
then may it please you with those songs
to solace my soul somewhat. For having
journey to hear together with my body,
it is weary. Love that discourses to me
in my mind. He then began to sing and
sang so sweetly that I still hear that
sweetness sound in me. My master, I and
all that company around the singer
seemed so satisfied, as if no other
thing might touch touch my our minds. We
all were motionless and fixed upon the
notes, when all at once the grave old
man cried out, "What have we here, you
lagarded spirits? What negligence? What
lingering is this?" Quick to the
mountain to cast off the slow that will
not let you see God show himself.
>> Okay, so um Dante sees an old friend
from Florence. Uh this friend has died.
Um, and they're very happy to see each
other. Okay, this is a contrast between
when uh Virgil and Ko saw each other.
Okay, they they reminisce. They they
talk about uh their past. Um and then Ko
sees him and says like like get out of
here. Stop lingering, right? Move on.
Okay. Um so uh there's a contrast here.
And again, Tonic does this a lot. Okay,
keep on going.
E line 124. Even as doves assembled
where they feed, quietly gathering their
grain or weeds, forgetful of their
customary strut, will if something
appears that makes them fear,
immediately leave their food behind
because they're assailed by greater
care. So did I see that new come
company. They left the song behind,
turned toward the slope like those who
go and yet do not know where. And we
were no less hasty in departure.
>> Let's continue. Okay.
Count to three. But while their sudden
flight was scattering those souls across
the plane toward the mountain where were
wrecked by rightful punishments, I drew
in closer to my true companion, for how
could I have run ahead without him? Who
could have helped me as I climbed the
mountain? He seemed like one who stung
by self-reproof. Oh pure and noble
conscience, you in whom each petty fault
becomes a harsh rebuke. And when his
feet had left off hurrying, for haste
denies all acts their dignity, my mind,
which was before too focused, were more
curious and widened its attention. I set
my vision toward the slope that rises
most deeply up to heaven from the sea.
Behind my back the sun was flaming red,
but there ahead of me its light was
shattered because its rays were resting
on my body. And when I saw the ground
was dark in front of me and me alone,
afraid that I had been abandoned, I
turned to my side. And he, my only
comfort, as he turned around began, why
must you still mistrust? Don't you
believe that I am with and guide you?
The body from within which I cast
shadows is buried where it now is
evening, take taken from Bundesi. It now
belongs to Naple.
Thus, if no shadow falls in front of me,
do not be more amazed than when you see
the heavens not impede each other's
rays. The power has exposed such
bodyless bodies to suffer torment, heat
and cold. How this is done, he would not
have us know. Foolish is he who hopes
our intellect can reach the end of that
unending road. Only one substance in
three persons follows. Confine yourself,
oh humans, to the qua. Had you been able
to see all, there would have been no
need for Mary to give birth.
>> Okay. Stop. Okay. All right. So, this is
actually a very important part of um
this poem. So, so I want to analyze it
uh in depth. Okay. First of all, explain
to me what the relationship now is
between Virgil and Dante. How would you
describe the relationship?
>> Yes.
like Dante's a little bit like a
teenager. So Virgils has given birth to
him and now he's looking at he still
really trusts him and likes him, but he
sees that he doesn't have a shadow. And
that's one of the ways that you know you
can climb the mountain because you're
walking towards your shadow trying to
deal with your sin.
>> And so he's thinking, how much of a
guide is he really going to be if he's
clearly not from here and he's not an
expert of this place? Um, okay. Um,
that's one way to interpret it, but I I
I kind of disagree with that. Okay. I I
I like, um, how does Donnie feel about
Virgil
when So, so again, the idea is that Don
has a body, so he's able to see his own
shadow. Virgil doesn't have a body, and
uh, you can't see a shadow. This is not
a problem in hell because there are no
shadows in hell. This is a problem here
in purgatory, right? Why is Dante upset
about not seeing Virgil Shadow?
>> Yes.
>> Dante maybe upset that he can feel that
he's getting close to
overtaking Virgil, outgrowing him.
>> No. No. Uh, yes. Um, Dante's very
insecure
and he felt that he's abandoned by
Virgil.
>> I think so. I think it's not I think
it's insecurity, right? It's it's like
like he needs Virgil constantly beside
him. He can't see the shadow. He's
nervous. Like, where's Virgil? And
Virgil like don't worry. I'm still with
you. I'm going to guide you. Relax, man.
Okay, that's exactly what what they're
saying here. Okay, does that make sense?
So it shows you how dependent Dante has
become on Virgil. It is Dante. It is
Virgil who lifted Dante out of hell and
now Dant is now dependent on Virgil to
lift him up to purgatory. Okay. And
again this is a pilgrimage. This is a
journey where Donnie has to learn to
become independent.
Um okay. Now a really important ters.
Okay. I I want you to focus on this
terset.
um
is
no 30 34
to 39. Okay, I want to focus on this.
This is like really important. Um
foolish is he who hopes or intellect can
reach the end of that unending road.
Only one substance in three persons
follows.
What is this referring to?
Trinity. But what is the one substance?
>> The monad.
>> Excuse me. the Monad.
>> Uh, no. The substance. What's the
substance? Love, right?
Who said
um, the Trinity is three persons and
they all have the same substance?
Who said that?
Dante. When Peter was asking him, "What
is faith? Do you believe in the Holy
Trinity?" He's like, "I do. I believe
that they that the trinity exists. They
all come from the same essence, which is
love." Okay.
So
this is what Dante will say in heaven.
Confine yourselves, oh humans, to
acquire. Have you not been receive all?
There would be have been no need for
Mary to give birth.
Okay. Have been no need for Mary to give
birth.
What?
What Virgil is saying is
um what no need for Mary to give birth.
What should what should he what what
could he say? What could he say instead
of this
or you know something much more
appropriate to Christian theology?
If we knew better then the there would
be no need for what to happen for Jesus
to come, right?
Why is it there would be no need for
Mary to give birth? Who who says this?
Who says this?
>> Dante.
>> Dante as well. Okay. Well, no actually
not Dante. Bernard says this in
paradise, right?
It is Mary giving birth. That is the
true miracle, not Jesus sacrificing
himself.
[snorts]
This is all coming from the mouth of
Virgil. Do you understand? And these
ideas will be presented to us in
paradise.
What's the paradox here?
>> Yes.
>> Where did he get to know these if what
he said in paradise was something that
he's supposed to learn from his journey?
>> Yeah. Like this is really confusing for
us because we just said Virgil is in
limbo and Virgil could possibly be the
master of hell. This is our speculation.
We don't have evidence this is the case.
How is it supposed been to paradise? How
is he able to know this stuff?
Right? We'll discover this stuff in
paradise, but we are in purgatory right
now. And Virgil has spent all eternity
in limbo. Where's he getting this stuff
from?
This is these are things that Donn will
discover once in heaven. But already
Virgil understands this stuff. How can
we explain this paradox?
Yeah, I just guess maybe Jesus got two
two side. One side is uh Jesus and other
side is is Lucifer. How about is it
possible?
>> Okay. So, you're saying that Virgil is
both Lucifer and Jesus?
>> That's that's interesting. Yes. Maybe
when he's saying foolish is he, he's
talking about himself in the past tense.
That um when he got brought out of
inferno, if he was there, that process
gave him the knowledge that ascension
requires faith in true love. Um but he
would didn't need to be told that. He
just because
But no, I'm trying to figure out how he
knows this stuff, right? He I I'm I'm
trying to figure out how he knows two
things that are revealed to us in
heaven. The first is that the Holy
Trinity is has one essence which is
love. So God is love basically, right?
Second thing is like he knows that Mary
is the one who redeemed us, not Jesus.
He knows this. So I'm saying how how
could he know this?
>> He was there.
>> He went there.
>> He went there. He was there.
>> He went there. And how did he end up in
in limbo?
Like you said, he chose us not to be
there. He was like, "Oh, this place is
great, but I have to be like a servant
to God. I don't want to do that, so I
just come back."
>> He could have gone there because he's
explicit, right? You cannot leave hell
unless Well, you you can't go to heaven
unless you're a Christian, right?
>> Uh yes.
>> Um did Beatatric tell him when she
assigned him the task?
>> Why would Beatric tell him this stuff?
>> Fine. I I'm like,
yes,
>> Dante guesses it and ascribes it to
Virgil. No, no, no, no. Virgil's a
teacher. Virgil's a father. Dante is a
student and a son, right? So, Dante
would never be as presumptuous as to
teach this to Virgil. And Dante does not
know this yet, right? He only knows this
when he goes up to heaven. So, how can
Virgil know this?
Well, technically Lucifer was really
close to God.
>> Right. Keep on going.
>> Right. So if and therefore he
understands the essence, the substance,
the three persons and therefore
I don't know a fragment of Lucifer is
with Virgil.
>> Okay,
that's a good start. Okay, that's very
close. Keep on going. Keep on going on
that logic. Yes.
>> For the devil to distort the truth means
that he knows the truth very well in its
fabrics to be able to tear it apart,
deconstruct it, cancel it.
>> Yes.
>> So then he probably revealed that to
Virgil like this is the essence, but we
were like try to divert.
>> Well, no, no, no, no. Okay. The first
part was right. The second part is like
>> you're assuming Lucifer talked to
Virgil, right? True, but he can't talk.
But Virgil can't Lucer can't talk. So
how does Virgil know this?
>> Yes.
>> It's the opposite of what happens of
what he sees of Lucifer in hell. So it's
like three sinners are digested into one
substance which is evil and that the
oppos it's the opposite of the
immaculate conception.
Okay. So that's an interesting theory.
Okay. And that explains the trinity. It
doesn't explain Mary.
Okay.
[snorts]
Who is Virgil?
What does he do? He's a poet. And who
are poets?
They're channeling God, right? You
understand? This is how Dante is able to
write this. He's channeling God. He
actually doesn't D probably doesn't even
know what he's writing. Okay. We
probably we're probably better at
analyzing this poetry than Dante. I mean
like I'm not exaggerating.
Donnie is just is just like singing the
truth of the universe. He doesn't really
know what he's singing. And that's what
a poet is. A poet is a vessel for the
divine fire.
Okay.
So
if Virgil knows this truth,
but he wrote the Iniad,
what is it saying about Virgil?
Do you mean
>> that Virgil Virgil is a is more or less
a Lucifer figure?
>> But why is he Lucifer?
>> Because he knows the truth. But truth to
know, to tell the truth.
>> No, no, no. Yes.
>> Well, I mean, in a way he was forced by
Augustus to
like speak poetry, but like um use it
for a empire way.
>> So, so in God's eyes, what did you do?
>> Well, he you betrayed God because
>> you betrayed God. You understand? The
great betrayer is Virgil, not Lucifer.
Okay, just think about this. Does that
make sense, guys? Because God gave you
the greatest gift possible, which is
poetry, which is divine and truth. And
you distorted it in order to serve
empire. That's the great betrayal,
right? Who's Lucifer? Lucifer is someone
who uh betrayed God in order to seek
power. Uh yes.
>> Then why is Virgil in me?
>> That's a really good question. Yes. Is
it because he left an Easter egg that
when Anias is about to kill Turnis, he
debates it a lot and then he sees
Palace's sword belt on Turnis and that's
what makes him finally kill him. But
that's we don't know whether that's
fully true or not, but at least it's
maybe Virgil saying that there was
another thing which made me make Anas
kill Turnis in the Anid. it wasn't just
the whole message that it seemed kind of
like a red herring that it was Palace's
sword belt that made him kill Tis when
it was his divine destiny to do so
anyway.
>> Okay, that's a good point. Okay, so like
try to visualize what's happening. Okay,
God gave Virgil the divine fire. Okay,
just as he's he gave uh Dante the divine
fire just as he gave Shakespeare the
divine fire. Okay, this is all divine
fire. This is not yours. This is God's.
Okay, and then Augustus says, "Okay, you
know what? give me that divine fire and
we'll craft a weapon together. Well, if
you do that, if you put the divine light
into the weapon, someone's going to leak
out. Does that make sense? And that's
why there's so many inconsistencies in
the iniad, including the one of where in
shows mercy or what show mercy the turn
is and then in the end decides to come
anyway. Okay? So, there are a lot of
inconsistencies in the iniad because
you're trying to weaponize divine fire
and divine fire does not want to be
weaponized. Okay?
It's meant to
uh like enlighten the world. It's not
meant to be directed as a weapon of
empire.
All right.
But
um
do do you guys do you guys understand
this this this idea that Virgil is the
great betrayer because God gave him
divine fire and rather than enlightening
the world like what Donnie is doing with
divine comedy, he she he chooses to
corrupt it in a way that serves empire
for his own personal benefit. And this
is a great betrayal of humanity. Right?
Imagine if Jesus came and he's like
screw this mission. I'm going to side
with the Romans. Yeah.
Right.
Yeah. Because like I don't be crucified
and the Romans are are going to give me
a trillion dollar. Screw screw this
mission, right?
Isn't that a great betrayal of God?
It's also a betrayal of humanity. Yes.
>> Yeah. And that's exactly what the Jews
hated Jesus for because they really
wanted a real messiah who was a militant
leader just like Julius Caesar. They
really wanted Jesus to side well not
side with the Romans or fight against
the Romans. That's why they denied him
the title of Messiah.
>> That's right. Exactly. Because Jesus was
a prophet of peace and they wanted a
prophet of war. Yes. Okay. Does that
make sense? So, so again when we
speculating but like again it's a huge
problem for us how these two ideas where
God is love and Mary is what redeemed
us. These are the two main ideas of
paradise. How are they appearing in the
mouth of Virgil right? And the answer is
well because he had access to divine
fire but he chose to corrupt it but it
doesn't answer the question is like how
did Virgil end up in limbo?
I think as a poet it's where he can be
the most creative because heaven is kind
of a place you can't touch or manipulate
whereas in hell he can create his own
story and also put who he wants in it.
>> Yes.
>> And like as we see hell is basically
created by Virgil and he knows the place
because he created it.
>> Exactly. Okay. So one explanation is
that Virgil created hell and Donna
created heaven. Okay. So ultimately
what's happening is a war between heaven
and hell. the a hell conceptualized by
Virgil and a and a heaven conceptualized
by Dante. That's one possibility. Yes.
Uh yes.
>> Yeah. So that's like a theory I had
about hell is that Dante is basically
entering
um Virgil's mind.
>> But he does enter Virgil's mind. How?
How?
>> Oh yeah, that's that's the point I don't
understand.
>> Okay. But how does he enter Virgil's
mind?
>> By going into hell or
>> No. No. No. How does he enter Virgil's
mind? In fact, he becomes Virgil's mind
because what did he do?
>> He read the Iniad.
>> He read the Iniad, right? That's what
the Iniad is. It's a mind of Virgil. It
is hell. Do you understand? It's a
blueprint for hell. Imagine a world in
which
love is a disease, right? And you can
just
kill any woman that you want. Okay?
Imagine a world without mercy, about
forgiveness, right? Your enemy, you must
kill. You can never show mercy to your
enemy. That is hell. No forgiveness, no
mercy, no love, just pure obedience.
That's what hell is. Okay. So
the iniad is the expression of hell and
divine comedy is expression of heaven.
But is it possible to read the vine
comedy without reading the iniad?
Is it possible? It's not possible
because you don't understand what's
going on. Okay? You understand? There
are lots of characters here and only by
reading the Iniad can you truly
appreciate Divine Comedy. So, heaven and
hell need each other. Okay? They're at
war with each other, but they also they
also need each other. They're
complimentary of each other. Okay? So,
that that's the other idea here. Okay?
But that still doesn't answer the So,
one possibility is okay, well, Virgil
created hell and Donna created heaven.
Okay, but how can we explain another how
can we further explain why Virgil is in
limbo and
not being punished for betraying God?
[snorts]
I'm not sure if we already answered this
in the last question, but could it just
be that Dante feels that he couldn't be
Dante without Virgil?
>> Right. So,
>> so he appreciates Virgil's contribution.
>> So, so that's that's a possibility,
right? Dante knows he cannot be done
without Virgil because and he says this
like he grew up being nourished and
nourished by the Iniad,
right? But why would that lead to Virgil
in limbo?
Okay. Yes. Virgil is still using
imagination, truth, beauty, and poetry.
So, it's still God's gift. So, because
he's using that, he's not going to be
punished. Still a creator.
>> No, no, no, no. That's even worse,
right? That that that's even worse. I
mean, if you don't know anything and you
you behave like and and you behave like
Virgil does, that's one thing. But like
to know that you're behaving the wrong
way and you still choose to do it,
that's that's, you know, that's um
that's even worse. Okay. All right. So,
let's think about this.
In the universe of Dante,
um where should Virgil be? Excuse
me.
>> In the inferno.
>> Which part of the inferno?
>> The very bottom in one of the mouths of
Satan.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. He's the great betrayer. Much
worse than Satan. He is the great
betrayer. And who's there instead?
>> Cas
>> and Buddhas. Right.
>> Yeah.
>> So, what do you think happened?
Again, we're only speculating. Okay.
Want to use our imagination. We're
trying to figure out how this system
works, right? Because in Dante's
framework,
Virgil, the place where he belongs is in
the mouth of Lucifer being chewed to
death because his betrayal is the same
as Lucifer's betrayal. Lucifer betrayed
God and Virgil betrayed humanity, right?
It's the INIAD that has condemned Europe
to a thousand years of hell. Just
endless war, endless suffering. Okay. No
mercy, no love.
Yes.
>> The Divine Comedy Inferno is not Dante's
framework, but Virgil's framework.
>> Right. Right. Right. Right. So, so
that's one possibility, but I'm saying
like let's another possibility, right?
Let's just say like Virgil is master of
hell. can he construct hell in any way
he wants and there's nothing that anyone
can do about it even God.
What's another possibility? Okay. And
the other possibility is okay. Let's go
with Donny's framework. And in Donny's
framework, um Virgil is in the bottom of
hell being chewed and tortured by
Lucifer.
How would he have gotten out of that
situation?
Uh yes,
>> only through Dante himself. Like Dante
himself puts Virgil into limbo because
he loves him so much maybe or he
forgives him.
>> Okay.
Right. Uh yes,
>> he got temporarily moved out by
Beatatrice and the other ladies from
heaven just for this purpose, but he
really doesn't want Dante to know that's
the truth. So he
>> possibility. Do you guys understand
that? You understand that? Because
Beatric has a problem, right? Beatric is
like Dante's lost in the woods. Someone
has to help him. And who's the only guy
possible? Virgil. Problem is Virgil is
in hell being chewed alive because of
his betrayal of humanity. But where? But
in the world, okay, who does Dante
admire the most? Who could guide Dante
out of hell?
Only Virgil, right? Because only Virgil
knows hell that much because he's at the
very bottom. So he understands the very
essence of hell. So they might have made
a deal, right? Where and this all
speculation, okay? But you can see how
this might work where Beatric says to
Virgil, "Okay, we'll give you a special
reprieve. You help Dante and then Dante
and and then we'll we'll you know uh
move your limbo and then we'll put in
British and castes in your in your
place." Does that make sense?
Metaphorically, it makes sense because
Dante probably wouldn't have written the
comedy without Virgil's influence.
>> Exactly. Exactly. Right. So, um,
tomorrow, uh, we talked to, um, David
Brahmich and David Brahmich had mentor
was Herold Bloom, right? And her Bloom
wrote a wrote a very famous book called
anxiety of influence.
And in the the very idea of anxiety of
influence is how is how does creation
happen? How is it possible for people
like Milton and Ke and Shakespeare to
create great arts of work uh create
create great uh artwork? And the answer
is anxiety of influence where as a young
poet you are so burdened by a higher
poet right so Milton was burdened by
Shakespeare and you think that oh it's
impossible for me to surpass him and you
try your very best to imitate him you
try you you try your very best to become
him but in this process
um of trying to become him you recognize
the problems in this and then you
develop your own creativity. Does that
make sense? You can't do it in a vacuum.
You can't do it in a blank slate. You
have to fully embrace someone and then
defeat that person, right? It it is very
similar to the fatherson dynamic, right?
Where you first become a father, then
you kill the father, then you become
yourself. Don't kill the father. Okay?
Don't kill your father, but like you
know, you leave your father behind. This
is what's happening right now. uh
literally between Virgil and Dante.
Okay, Dante has become Virgil's son and
he's trying to become Virgil, but in the
process he will discover the pro the
limitations of um Virgil and become his
own poet. Okay, does that make sense?
And it's very similar to the way I teach
where you know in the first few days I
was trying to give you a lot of ideas
but over time um as you have your as you
have this framework that I I given you
this framework allows you to better
analyze the divine comedy and over time
if you keep on doing this you'll
discover I can build my own framework I
don't need this for framework anymore
but you first need that framework okay
does that make sense all Right?
Does that answer answer your question?
Okay. All right. And again, we're only
speculating. Okay. We're only using our
imagination. But you can see how this
does explain a lot about what's going
on, right?
And again, what's really confusing right
now is these two great truths of
paradise. Um, Virgil already knows. It
also shows you the consistency, the
totality of Divine Comedy, right? where
all three inferno, purgatory, and
paradise all line up perfectly. And I
don't know how you could do that as a
human being. And this is an age before
computers. This is an age even before
like pen and paper, right? But he's able
to do this in his mind.
And if you're like, well, it's all him
being deliberate and being very careful.
Well, that doesn't really get you
anywhere. But if you're like, okay, all
he's doing is channeling the divine
fire. Well, that explains a lot more.
Okay. Okay. Does that make sense, guys?
All right. All right. Uh, let's keep on
reading.
>> Line 40. You saw the fruitless longing
of those men who would, if reason, could
have been content, those whose desire
eternally laments. I speak of Aristotle
and of Plato and many others. Here he
bent his head and said no more,
remaining with his sorrow. By this time
we had reached the mountains base,
discovering a wall of rock so sheer that
even agile legs are useless there. The
loneliest, most jagged promonter that
lies between Turbia and Larichi compared
with it could provide stairs wide and
easy. Now who knows where along this
mountain side? My master Halang asked,
one finds arise where even he who has no
wings can climb.
>> Wait, stop. Okay. All right. Um, so he
says, you saw the fruitless longing of
those men who would, if reason could
have been content, those who desire
eternally laments. I speak of Aristotle,
Plato and many others. What does he mean
by this?
What does he mean by this? Yes.
That because they didn't know about the
Trinity and those special truths of
heaven, they even though they had great
souls and pure souls, they were just
eternally desiring to understand the
Mona but hadn't been given the special
the two special truths well of the
immaculate conception and trinity. So
even though they probably should have
made it, they're the ones the most upset
that they had.
>> Yeah, that's close. Okay, but I I would
phrase it differently. Does anyone else
want to try?
Yeah, you can try again.
just that
they still have a distance between them
and the world of the forms. What if you
think that's where God resides?
>> Sure. Sure. But we're trying to figure
out what causes this distance. Okay.
What causes this separation?
>> They didn't reason and knowledge.
>> They didn't think they needed faith.
>> I It's faith, right? Because explain to
me because only with faith do you
understand that it's miracle redeemed
us, not Jesus. It's only with faith that
you understand that God is love. Okay?
You can't prove it. You can't reason it
out. Plato and Aristotle their problem
was that they wanted to reason out. You
can't do that. You you have to have
faith and from this faith comes your
imagination which then allows you to
access the the truth. Do you understand
the logic? And again, it's amazing
because
this is what because this is what Donnie
will tell us will reveal to us in
paradise. You need to you need to live a
life of faith, hope, and love. And
Virgil is already saying this. So Virgil
knows this but he refuses to act it out.
Okay. He refuses to align uh will with
action.
Okay. All right. Let's keep on reading.
>> While he his eyes upon the ground
consulted his mind considering what road
to take. And I looked up around the wall
of rock. Along the left a band of souls
appeared to me to be approaching us. But
so unheardly their movements did not
show. Lift up your eyes, I told my
master, "Here are those who can advise
us how to go if you can find no counsel
in yourself." At this he looked at them
and less distressed, replied, "Let us go
there. Their steps are slow, and you, my
gentle son, hold fast to hope." The
distance from that company to us, I
mean, when we had gone a thousand paces
was still as far as the fine hurler's
toss. when they all huddled toward the
hard rock wall and once they had crowded
there refused to budge even as men when
apprehensive halt "Oh chosen souls you
have ended well." Virgil began by virtue
of that peace which I believe awaits you
all. Please tell us where the slope
inclines and can be climbed. For he who
best discerns the worth of time is most
distressed whenever time is lost. Even
as sheep that move, first one, then two,
then three out of the fold, the others
also stand, eyes and muzzles lowered
timidly. And what the first sheep does,
the others do, and if it halts, they
huddle close behind, simple and quiet,
and not knowing why. So then I saw those
spirits in the front of that flock
flavored, favored by good fortune move.
Their looks were modest, seemly, slow,
their walk. As soon as these souls saw
upon my right along the ground a gap in
the sun's light where shadows stretched
from me to the rock wall, they stopped
and then drew back somewhat. And all who
came behind them, though they they did
not know why those ahead had halted,
also slowed.
Without your asking, I shall tell you
plainly that you're looking at a human
body. That's why the sunlight on the
ground is broken. Don't be astonished.
rest assured that he would not attempt
to cross this wall without a force that
have incentive and support. These were
my master's words that worthy band
replied, "Come back and move in our
direction." And gestured with backhanded
motions, right? And one of them began,
"Whoever you may be, as you move
forward, turn and see. Consider if
beyond you've ever seen me." I turned to
look at him attentively. He was
fairhired and handsome, and his aspect
was noble. But one eyebrow had been
clefted by a swordstroke. When I had
humbly noted that I had never seen him,
he said, "Look now," showing me a wound
high on his chest. Then, as he smiled,
he told
he told me, "I'm Manfred, the grandson
of the Empress Constance. Thus, I pray
that when you reach the world again, you
may go to my lovely daughter, mother of
kings of Sicily and Aragon. Tell her the
truth, lest she's heard something
other." After my body had been shattered
by two fatal blows and tears, I then
consigned myself to him who willingly
forgives. My sins were ghastly, but the
infinite goodness has armed so wide that
it accepts whoever would return,
imploring it. As if Cazenza's bastard,
who was sent to hunt me down, alive or
dead by Clement, had understood this
facet of God's mercy, my body's bones
would still be there beneath the custody
of the great heap of stones near
Benavvento at the bridge head. Now rain
bathes my bones. The wind has driven
them beyond the kingdom near the verd's
banks where he transported them with
tapers bent. Despite the church's curse,
there's no one so lost that the eternal
love cannot return as long as hope shows
something green. But it is true that
anyone who dies in contacency of the
holy church, though he repented at the
end, must wait along the shore for 30
times the span he spent in his
presumptuousness.
Unless that edict is abridged through
fitting prayers. Now see if you by
making known to my kind constants where
you saw my soul and wide delays decreed
for me can make me happy. Those here
through those beyond advance more
quickly.
>> Okay. So um they are moving towards
purgatory. They are anti purgatory.
Right? So they not yet enter the gates
of purgatory and they're meeting
different souls and one of them is
Manfred. Now Manfred um is a royal. He
is a king. He's a grandson of the
emperor's constants
and uh he died in battle and he was
excommunic ex communicated by the
church. Why is this a paradox?
He was excommunicated by the church. Why
is this a paradox
>> is here?
>> Yeah, it's straight go. It's like go
straight to hell card, right? You're
excommunicated. It means that you have
been banished from the community of
Christians. Doesn't matter if you're
baptized, doesn't matter what you
believe, doesn't matter what you do. You
have now been banished from the
community of Christianity. And
therefore, you must now burn in hell.
Um,
and what does Manfred say?
How can we understand this this? Yes.
>> He said as I was dying basically in
tears, I suddenly was like, "God, please
forgive me." And then I know my sins
were terrible, but God, you know, spread
his arms to me to to return. Um, yeah.
>> So God is all forgiving. Okay, you have
a direct connection to God. And okay, if
you get ex excuited by the church,
that's bad. But but that just means you
spend more time in purgatory. Okay.
Right. So again, this is revolutionary
for this time in history where the ex
exccommunication doesn't really matter
that much. Okay? What matters is your
faith in God. Um,
how is it possible to reduce your time
in purgatory? Do you guys know? Yes.
>> Someone who's alive prays for you.
>> Exactly. Okay. Right. This goes back to
the idea in heaven where um if an infant
dies, but the parents are very virtuous
and pray for the infant. The infant is
given access to heaven. Yes.
>> I think it also matters whether the
prayer is like a good prayer or just
like an off-handed prayer. I think
there's like a difference between
>> yeah no no no commitment right you know
if someone's praying for you um eight
hours a day and also the number of
people also matter as well like if
entire community is praying for you that
will reduce your time in in purgatory
okay right okay all right so let's keep
on going
Kanto four. When any of our faculties
retains a strong impression of delight
or pain, the soul will wholly
concentrate on that, neglecting any
other power it has. And this refutes the
error that maintains that one above the
other, several souls can flame in us.
And thus, when something seen or heard
secures the soul in stringent grip, time
moves, and yet we do not notice it. The
power that perceives the course of time
is not the power that captures all the
mind. The former has no force, the
latter binds. And I confirmed this by
experience, hearing that spirit and my
wonderment. For though the sun had fully
climbed 50°, I had not noticed it. And
when we came to the point at which in
unison those souls cried out to us,
"Here's what you want."
>> Okay. So at this this answers your
question of time, right? You have a
question about time. What does Dante
say?
Right. So, but what does he mean?
Right. We had a question about time,
right? So, what does Donnie say about
time?
Yes.
>> The sun has climbed 50°.
>> Yeah. And that's physical time.
But what
could could you um Yeah. What what's he
saying here?
>> Um well uh verse 10. The power that
perceives the course of time is not the
power that captures all the mind. The
former has no forth. The latter binds.
So um it's not your perception. It's
your imagination.
>> It's not the perception that matters.
What matters?
The perception of time doesn't matter.
>> The emotions. Right. Right? So the power
that cap perceives the course of time is
not the power that captures all the
mind. Okay? The power that perceives the
course of time has no force. The power
that captures all the mind which is the
emotions that binds. Okay.
>> All right. So what matters is the
emotional time as as opposed to the
physical time. Okay. Keep on going.
Line 13. And I confirmed this by
experience, hearing that spirit in my
wonderment. For though the sun had fully
climbed 50 degrees, I had not noticed
it. When we came to the point at which
in unison, those soul cried out to us,
"Here's what you want." And then verse
19, "The farmer, when the grape is
darkening, will often stuff a wider
opening with just a little forkful of
his thorns." Then was the gap through
which my guide and I which followed
after climbed with two alone after the
company of souls had gone.
>> Why does he notice the passing of time?
Why does he notice the passing of time?
>> Yes,
>> the changing of the sun's degrees.
>> Well, well, that would tell him the
time, but he doesn't even notice that.
I'm saying why doesn't he notice the
sun, the time, the passing of time?
And like this is just like like why
don't you notice time?
Does your perceiving change?
>> Uh, yes.
>> Um,
>> why would you not notice time?
>> Not notice time?
>> Yeah. What would you not notice time
>> if nothing changes in?
>> You know what I'm saying? Like like when
do you not notice time? Yes.
>> You're sleeping
>> that you lost your
>> Yeah. When you're happy. Okay.
>> When you're happy. And why sounding very
happy?
Why you sounding happy?
What?
>> He's on his way to Beatatrice.
>> No, there's a better reason.
>> He hasn't mentioned Beatatric yet.
He's out of hell, right?
>> Oh,
>> okay. He He was in hell and now he's
finally out of hell. His son, there's
people who are happy. He's just He's
just really happy right now. Okay. All
right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> Verse 25. Then Leo can be climbed. One
can descend to Noli and ascend Kakume
and Bispantova with feet alone. But here
I had to fly. I mean with rapid wings
and pinions of immense desire behind the
guide who gave me hope and with my
light. We made our upward way through
rifted rock along each side the edges
pressed on us. The ground beneath
required feet and hands. When we had
reached the upper rim of that steep
bank, emerging on the open slope, I
said, "My master, what way shall we
take?" And he to me, "Don't squander any
steps. Keep climbing up the mountain
after me until we find some expert
company. The summit was so high my sight
fell short. The slope was far more steep
than the line drawn from middle quadrant
to the center point. I was exhausted
when I made this plea. Oh gentle father,
turn around and see. I will not left
alone. I will be left alone alone unless
you halt. My son, he said, draw yourself
up to there while pointing to a somewhat
higher terrace which circles all the
slope along that side. His words incited
me. My body tried. On hands and knees, I
scrambled after him until the terrace
lay beneath my feet. There we sat down
together, facing east in the direction
from which we had come. What joy to look
back at a path we've climbed. My eyes
were first set on the short below, and
then I raised them toward the sun. I was
amazed to find it fall upon our left.
And when the poet saw that I was struck
with wonder as I watched the chariot of
light passing between the north and us,
he said to me, "Suppose Caster and Pix
were in conjunction with that mirror
there, which takes the light and guides
it north and south. Then you would see
the reddish zodiac still closer to the
bears as it revolved, unless it has
abandoned it track." If you would
realize how that should be, then
concentrate imagining this mountain so
placed upon this earth that both mount
Zion and it although in different
hemispheres share one horizon.
Therefore, you can see putting your mind
to it attentively.
>> Where is Mount Zion? You guys know
where's Mount Zion?
I'll be in
Mount Zion. Come on, guys. In Israel,
>> Egypt.
Jerusalem, right? Zionist. Come on, man.
Zionist, right? Mount Zion. So, what
what what he's saying is that purgatory
and Jerusalem
are opposite of each other. Does that
make sense?
Okay. So, um
yeah. Uh yeah. What is relationship
between Dante and Virgil?
How would you describe the relationship?
Suie.
No.
Yes.
>> Well, still a father-son relationship.
>> Yes. Can you explain why?
>> Well, like further up, he he said Virgil
said uh son to Dante and Dante said
father to Virgil.
>> Okay. So, and they and he Dante still
trusts Virgil that he knows the way up.
>> So, let's imagine you're a father, okay?
Right. And you take your son who's like
10 on a hike to a mountain, right?
What's your son doing all the time?
>> Are we there yet?
>> Yeah. Are we there yet? Okay. And what's
doing like are we there yet? Okay. And
and and the father's like, "Oh, like you
know, just focus on the mountain top."
Okay. So, so it's very much a a
father-son relationship. And it's almost
like Dante has regress, right? because
he's acting a lot more im immaturely
than before, right? Before it was one of
respect, uh, one of awe at Virgil. Now
it's just like, are we there yet, man?
This is so exhausting. And V is like,
come on, man. Move it. Okay. All right.
Let's keep on going.
>> Um, line 71. Line 71. Therefore you can
see putting your mind to it attentively
how that same path which Fan drove so
poorly must pass this mountain on the
north whereas it skirts Mount Zion on
the southern side. I said, "My master,
surely surely I have never since my
intelligence seemed lacking, seen as
clearly as I now can comprehend that the
midcircle of the heavens motion, one of
the sciences call it equator, which
always lies between the sun and winter,
as you explained, lies as far north of
here, as it lies southward of the sight
from which the Hebrews looking toward
the tropics saw it. But if it pleased
you, I should willingly learn just how
far it is we still must journey. The
slope climbs higher than my eyes can
follow." and he to me this mountains of
such sort that climbing it is hardest at
the start but as we rise the slope grows
less unkind. Therefore when this slope
seems to you so gentle then climbing
farther up will be as restful as
traveling downstream by boat. You'll be
where this pathway ends and there you
can expect to put your weariness to
rest. I say no more and this I know is
true.
>> Okay, so again Donis is bitching
throughout this, right? He's like, "Are
we there yet? I'm so exhausted. Can we
just rest?" And then Virgil's like,
"Come on, we're almost there."
Um, why u, and I don't actually know the
answer to this question. Why is Virgil
uh and Donnie, why are they spending so
much time on trying to geollocate where
they are, right? Like they're they're
very explicit about where they are.
Like, okay, we have the we are the
opposite end of Jerusalem. The stars are
like this. Why would why would um Bonnie
spend so much time trying to geollocate
Mount Purgatory? And I don't actually
know the answer. Yes.
>> To like be more accurate while he's
writing the poem because he's going to
like teach all of these to the people.
>> Uh yes, you could know where heaven
touches the earth.
I.e. the peak of the mountain would be
the closest place on earth to heaven.
Yeah, I I understand that. But like
purgatory is made up, right? So, I'm
trying to figure out why he's trying to
be so exact and detailed about where
Mount Purgatory is. Yes.
>> Well, you're hiking, right? So, um try
to memorize all the signs and where
things are so that you don't get lost.
>> Okay, I understand that. Um yes.
>> Is it just a metaphor for purgatory?
Because purgatory is quite a meticulous
place where you have to clean
yourselves.
>> Right. Right. Right. But I'm I'm trying
to figure this out. Okay. I'm trying to
figure out why he's spending so much
time
being so exact and detailed about where
Mount Purgatory is, what it looks like,
what where is in relation to other
places. What why would he again? I don't
actually know the answer. I'm just
asking you this question.
Uh yes,
>> maybe Dentine just uh did the trust
distrust of Virgil. He say maybe Virgil
try to treat him or
>> Well, it's Virgil is doing the talking.
I guess
>> maybe Virgil's trying to remember it for
later. When his task with Dante is done,
he gets shoved back to limbo/hell and
he's trying just to remember for
himself.
>> That's a very optimistic reading of
Virgil actually. Yes.
>> The way to measure things. So because
it's about progress, you can only
progress in what you measure. So they're
looking at where they are like to start
with and then progress with it.
>> Yeah. Okay. Right. Good. Right. So um
maybe a possibility is like they're
trying to give people a sense of time so
like their progress can be tracked.
Okay. That's one really strong
possibility. Yes. And I I don't know the
answer. I'm just like what are
possibilities here? Just use your use
your imagination. Anyone else? Yes.
Well, maybe just for the reader so you
can imagine it as detailed as possible.
And and why would that why would that be
important?
>> I find this to be a treasure map for
imagination,
>> right? Because um back to your point
about Dante starting ushering in
Renaissance, if you look at Renaissance
paintings, there are lots of
perspectives.
>> Mh.
>> And um it's almost like if you want to
imagine to the fullest, you need to give
details. A lot of details.
>> Yes.
>> And this is like a treasure map to hey,
this is how you do it.
>> Yes. And I guess that's why maybe a
cultist and you know later people would
find this enlightening because literally
this is a map
>> to the ultimate treasures.
>> Yes. Yes. Okay.
>> Like a hiker you probably know the
Japanese like commando kodo which is shy
which is one of the pilgrimage roads by
UNESCO saying that it's a pilgrimage. So
you go through the mountains to you know
purify your soul and all that. The other
one is the one uh the route of San Diego
the compostella which is another trip to
um to pilgrimage through the mountains
and stuff. And so maybe in his idea that
like this idea of purgatory purging
yourself as you hike or as you you know
go on a journey itself physically
metaphorically it's a way to purify
yourself just like Muslims also go to
you know the same.
>> Okay. So um I think that Carol's point
is very interesting. So let's drop some
paintings. Okay. Let's look at um
medieval European art. Okay. And then
we're going to contrast that with
Renaissance art and see if we can spot
the difference. Actually, it's actually
pretty blatant, but but we'll do it.
Okay. Medieval art. We'll we'll look at
some images. Okay. Okay. So, this is
medieval art, guys. Okay. All right. Do
you guys see that?
Uh just put it put it in your mind. Now,
we're going to do Renaissance art. And
again, the difference is pretty stark.
>> What's the difference, guys?
>> Yes. Yes. Go ahead. Go ahead.
>> Yes. So, space and time really matter
here. Yes.
>> Yeah. From from two-dimensional to
three-dimensional.
>> Yes. Right. It's pretty obvious, right?
They put a lot of focus on space and
time on death perception. Right. Before
it was 2D, now it's 3D.
Any anyone else?
>> It's a de it's a demonstration of
imaginative power. uh this um to uh
convey the force of divine imaginative
power you you do have to have uh you
know very very uh you know deep
knowledge about geography but also
imagination.
>> Yes. So let's do mathematics of
renaissance art. Let's see what what
what happens if we do that. Mathematics
of Renaissance art.
Yeah. So, they're using a lot of
mathematics with Renaissance art, right?
Um the um maybe the Last Supper. Okay.
This is Divine Comedy.
Okay. Well, I mean this is Yeah.
Yeah.
Okay. But you guys see this? Okay.
There's there's a lot more mathematics
in Renaissance art than there is in
medieval art. In fact, there's really no
mathematics in medieval art. But but if
you look at but you look at Renaissance
art, the geometry really matters. The
symmetry really matters. Dep perception
really matters. Okay. And this started
because of Dante. Dante is really
concerned about mathematics. He's really
trying he's really concerned about
trying to create as much detail as
possible in his poetry so that excites
the imagination. Okay. And it makes it
Yes.
>> And also pretty much every Renaissance
painting is like a historical moment in
time. And the medieval paintings were
just like bishops and like just
portraits. But this is like really Yeah.
This really ignites the imagination like
you you can like imagine yourself
sitting at the table or like
>> Right. Yeah. And and and why would it
excite the imagination as opposed to uh
medival art? Yes.
>> Because you're grounding it in something
more naturalistic and you're able to see
yourself more. And I think the reason he
does it in purgatory is cuz you can kind
of go on purgatory a little bit while
you're alive in real life.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? Okay. Right.
So you can actually imagine yourself
taking a hike and looking at the stars
and then that draws you back to the
divine comedy and when you read divine
comedy you can also pick you can also as
you read this imagine yourself with
Virgil and Dante climbing up mount
preparatory that's a power of detail and
precision again again guys this is
really it's obvious to us now but this
is re it's it's watching it's literally
watching a movie yes
>> well I really feel like purgatory is
really similar to just Earth in general,
you know, like we have a sun, we have,
you know, it's really like earthlike as
as opposed to inferno,
>> right? And he's trying to make it as
earthlike as possible, right? By by by m
by geoloccating it and says like this is
actually a real place
>> on on on on Earth, right? And so again,
we're not transitioning from the
medieval period to the Renaissance
period. And this is what sparks it
because of its h um humanistic
qualities, right? Its willingness to
draw you into the story, its realism. So
that you feel that Mount Purgatory is a
real place. If it's a real place, then
um it gives you hope, right? Because
before you you believe that there's only
hell and and heaven and now like no,
there's a there's a purgatory place and
it's a transition into heaven. So even
if you screwed up, as long as you're
willing to repent, you will go to
purgatory and you'll be there for a
million years. You'll be there for
thousand thousand years. Who knows? But
hey, if your family really loves you,
you know, it won't be as bad. Okay? So
it's getting it's almost incentivizing
you to live life to the fullest, to live
a life of love, to show kindness,
generosity, and mercy to others. Right?
Okay. And again, this is opposite of the
iniat, right? way again. You're not
supposed to show mercy to your enemies
where you're not supposed to like fall
in love. You're just you're just
supposed to like obey the gods. Does
that make sense, guys? All right. All
right. Let's keep going.
97. And when his words were done,
another voice nearby was heard to say,
"Perhaps you will have need to sit
before you reach that point." Hearing
that voice, both of us turned around and
to the left we saw a massive boulder
which neither he nor I before had
noticed. We made our way toward it and
toward the people who lounged behind
that boulder in the shade as men beset
by a listlessness will rest and one of
them who seemed to me exhausted were
sitting with his arms around his knees.
Between his knees he kept his head bent
down. Oh my sweet lord, I said, look
carefully at one who shows himself more
languid than he would have been where
laziness his sister. Then that shade
turned toward us attentively, lifting
his eyes but just above his thigh and
said, "Climb then, if you're so
vigorous, then I knew who he was." And
the distress that still was quickening
quickening my breath somewhat, did not
prevent my going to him. And when I had
reached him, scarcely lifting up his
head, he said, "And have you fathomemed
how the sun can drive his chariot on
your left?" The slowness of his
movements, his brief words, had stirred
my lips a little toward a smile. than I
began. From this time on, Balacqua, I
did I need not grieve for you. But tell
me, why do you sit here? Do you expect a
guide, or have you fallen into your old
ways? And he, oh brother, what's the use
of climbing? God's angel, he who guards
the gate, would not let me pass through
to meet my punishment. Outside that
gate, the skies must circle around as
many times as they did when I left,
since I delayed good until the end.
Unless before then I am helped by prayer
that rises from a heart that lives in
grace. What use are other prayers
ignored by heaven? And now the poet
climbed ahead before me and said, "It's
time. See the meridian touched by the
sun. Elsewhere along the ocean, night
now has set its foot upon Morocco."
>> Okay. All right. So, um we we will
conclude uh um today. Um a reminder
tomorrow morning we start at 9:00
exactly. Okay. Try to come at 8:50. We
have a very special uh guest. We're very
honored to have him. Professor David
Brahmich who was doing professor of
English at um Yale. Um his mentor was
Herold Bloom. Of course I I didn't
mention that. Um and he will come and
talk to us about McBth. He's joining us
live from New Haven. Um, and then we
will have a discussion
uh about Shakespeare and Dante, how
they're similar, how they're different.
Uh, and it'll be a very uh interesting
conversation.
Um, so um yeah, it'll go on for about an
hour and then we'll continue reading
Purgatory and we'll try to do about 10.
Okay, we have like three days more. We
have three days left and we'll try to do
10 10 10. Okay. Um, so please review
what we've learned. Any questions about
about today before we we end?
Any questions, guys?
Ask one question then we'll end. Okay.
Yes. Uh very general question, but do
you think uh open and free imagination
is compatible with organiz organiz
organizing a society? because it seems
like once a society reaches a certain
amount of people and a level of
organization, then you need to force
people into imagining that your system
works.
>> That's a great question. Okay. Um, and
quite honestly, if Dante were alive
today, he could not possibly understand
why we live the way we do, right? We
live in cities of 10 million people. Oh,
Beijing is like what 25 million people,
but like no one knows each other and
like you're just like you're just like a
little cog in the machine and like D
would be like what's the point of this
existence, right? What are you guys
trying to accomplish with this sort of
with existence
um back then in Italy? Whatever the
issues were, at least people knew each
other, okay? And at least people had
roots. At least people knew why they
were they were living. And um happiness
had a purpose, right? You wanted your
community to thrive. And now in our
world, we're just focused all on just
material acquisition. And as you point
out, that's a result of mass society.
Okay. Once your society reaches a
certain point, your society has to be
organized a certain way. Um you lose
your sense of community. You lose your
sense of identity. You are just a um
empty soul. Um you're basically like
you're basically a slave really. Okay.
Okay. I mean, like, I hate to say this,
but like, are we not slaves? I mean, I
like just the idea of like sending kids
to school to learn to read and write so
that they can go to university to get to
get a useless degree so that they can go
make useless money, right? I mean, like
what exactly is the point? All right.
So, um, as you point out, once society
reaches a certain number, it it could be
a million, it could be two million, who
knows? Okay. But you're kind of stuck
like this and there's no way out of it
because uh with this with this amount of
people you need bureaucracy and you need
hierarchy and you need inequality in
order to make the society function.
There's really no way around it. But
it's an interesting question and it's
something that I want to discuss at the
end of this class, right? And and the
question then is if Dante were to come
today, first of all, how would he feel
about us? He'd be and the answer is he'd
be pretty disgusted. but also what would
Dante recommend that we do? Okay, what
are some paths forward given the
structure of society today? So, thanks
for the question and and we'll come back
to it um later on.